him because he recognized that his behavior at the time had been unacceptable.
During the meal, Kevin was thankful for the food and the people he knew at the mission.
He mentioned some names as well. A meal at the mission means to share a moment with each other,
to share the dignity of being alive. Kevin's soul needs more prayer. That's what we know,
and the community will be praying for him. We don't know if this will ever take away the sense
of defeat we're experiencing now. One thing we know that is if God ever takes time to invite Kevin
over for dinner. Kevin will be thankful and
He will receive with gratitude whatever God will offer him.
The icon of the Trinity we know has an empty place at the table.
If God ever invites Kevin, Kevin would not refuse and he would know how to behave in his presence
with gratitude, asking for forgiveness and being thankful for any good thing that touched
his life.
That's the truth we know and we'll always remember.
Thank you for listening to our parables of community, asceticism of the open door.
is parable.
are the precious pearls that God bestows on the church when it risks opening its door to the stranger.
We hope that they will inspire you to discover the presence of the kingdom in your own
parishes and life.
This has been a listener-supported presentation of Ancient Faith Radio.
Glory to Jesus Christ, glory forever, you're listening to ancient faithradio.com.
He will be a staff for the righteous, with which for them to stand and not to fall.
And he will be the light of the nations and the hope of those whose hearts are troubled.
All who dwell on the earth will fall down and worship him, and they will praise and bless,
and celebrate with song the Lord of Spirits.
1st denoc.
Chapter 48.
Verses 4 through 5.
The modern world doesn't acknowledge but is nevertheless haunted by spirits, angels,
demons, and saints.
In our time, many year into break free of the prison of a flat, secular materialism,
to see and to know reality as it truly is.
What is this spiritual reality like?
How do we engage with it well?
How do we permeate everyday life with spiritual presence?
Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew Stephen Damick, and Father Stephen De Young
host this live Colin show, focused on enchantment in creation,
the union of the scene and unseen as made by
God and experienced by mankind throughout history.
Welcome to the Lord of Spirits.
Good evening.
It's the 33rd episode of the Lord of Spirits podcast
and the last episode of 2021.
My co-host Father Stephen D'Young is with me
from Lafayette, Louisiana,
and I'm Father Andrew Stephen Damick
in Emeas, Pennsylvania.
And if you're listening to us live,
you can call in at 855 AF radio,
Let's eat 5.5.2.
237, 2346, Matyska Trudy will be taking your calls tonight and we're going to get to
those in the second part of our show.
So in the prophets ascend in heavenly visions, they see the divine counsel, the throne of
God, the cherubim, the seraphim, the angels, and a man.
And sometimes outside of prophetic visions that man shows up on earth and he talks and
even eats with people.
Who is this man in heaven?
Who is this man?
from heaven. Well tonight we're going to wrap up our four-part series on the
Christology of the Old Testament. In our first episode we looked at the title, the
Angel of the Lord, and the second it was the Word of the Lord or the Word of God.
And the last time we looked at the phrase, the Son of Man, all of these
appear in the Scriptures and get used by the fathers and the divine services.
So tonight we're going to look at, well almost everything else from the
testament where God appears in some kind of physical form, but especially in a human form to us, his creatures.
Father Stephen, I was told that no one has ever seen God ever, like ever, ever. So what's going on?
Except for all the times that they do.
do. Exactly. Yes, it is the the eve of Christmas Eve. Yes, Christmas Eve. Yes. And so this is our Christmas Eve eve.
episode. Christmas Eve squared. Yeah. And I want to I want to I want to try something.
Okay. I'm because the revival of Dexter at the beginning of each episode,
they show us a quick succession these one second clips from later in the episode.
Oh, right. To like tease what's going to happen and get you interested. Okay.
So I want to tell people that if they stay tuned tonight, they will hear about the
pleasing man.
They will hear about the Cherubim Zodiac.
And they will get another example of why time and space don't exist.
There we go. So stick with us everyone.
Yes. So that's what awaits you.
Yes. And as you're about to found your new Prague Rock band,
you can call your lead singer Cherubim Zodiac.
Yes. Yes. You can find a way to work. Call your first album,
pleasing man. You can work this all.
Um, so yeah.
Yeah, and one of the ways of talking about this that we've mentioned way back in the episode
about God's body, which was what like the fifth or sixth episode or something?
I don't even remember. No, it was it was early this year, but but we had done a few months. Yeah,
we had done a few months of stuff. Yeah, yeah, yeah. It all blurs together. Anyway. It does.
So we talked about this term.
that was used, well, sort of attempted to be repurposed
by St. Mark the Ascetic, or sometimes called St. Mark the Monk,
Kiriakos Anthropos in Greek.
Yeah, he shows up in the Filokalia, right?
Right.
And that gets sort of brought through Latin
as the Dominican man or the Lordly man is the idea.
Now that term, I say he attempted to repurpose it,
because that term was used by the Apollinarians.
to describe sort of their composite Christology.
Yeah, right.
And St. Mark tried to sort of take the terminology
and repurpose it, and it didn't really catch on.
Right.
So the other father, other later fathers
didn't sort of pick up on it and use it the way he did.
But it was a way for him to talk about
the in-scare quotes pre-incarnate Christ,
more on that later.
places where the second person of the Holy Trinity outside of the incarnation in the
New Testament appears in bodily form, right?
It seems to have some sort of particularly human bodily form.
And that was a trick, which I think if the Appalainarians hadn't already used it probably
would have caught on and been helpful.
But yeah, I mean, it's a pretty good phrase.
Yeah, just reading it literally.
Anthropos, Lordly Man, or, you know, yeah. Yeah, I mean, it works, but unfortunately,
politics got a hold of it and wouldn't let go. Poisoned the will. Yes. Right. Yeah. So,
tonight we're going to kind of be going through some passages in some detail as is our want.
cause there are a few sort of key passages and as you also mentioned this is
this is kind of
Well, the last three episodes were very, well, for us tightly themed.
This one we're going to touch on a lot more stuff along the way.
That's maybe not directly related, but because we're going to be working through these
passages there are going to be other sort of related things that come into play that we'll
talk about.
Yes, although I should say by the way though, we did get a comment from someone that described
our last episode as quote a red
tortuous and winding journey around the issue. Oh, that's cool. Yeah, so not everybody thinks it was
very focused. Those are my favorite comments. Well, that's why I put it before us. Yeah, for us exactly.
Yes, for us. It was good. Yeah, I mean, I, you know, I think that part of the reason that it
that it comes to be that way is that if we just simply say, okay, here's the question and here's
Here's the answer, goodnight everybody, that we miss the way that the answer
needs to be received, right? And often there's a whole lot of, you know, unlearning what
you have learned kind of thing that we have to do along the way. So I don't know, I'm
not going to make any apologies for our rather torturous and winding journey around the
issue. But God bless you, reviewer. Thank you very much for that. Yeah. Yeah. I mean, that
reminds me of someone someone asked Alfred Hitchcock once why nobody in his movies ever called
the police and he said, question because then the movie would be
over in five minutes and that would be boring.
Was his response, right?
So, yeah, come on, man.
How it should have ended.
Have some periods of issues.
Have some fun.
Exactly.
We're all here to have a good time.
It's right here, here, song lyrics from they might get giants.
Get true, get true to home late for dinner.
Yeah.
Right.
That's our goal.
So, okay.
Well, the first day back to Daniel 10,
back to Dana's prophesies.
Back to Daniel, yeah.
So yeah, the first, the first one of these texts that we're going to go through in some detail is
From Daniel chapter 10 we spent a lot of time in and around
Daniel seven last time and we've sort of gone through Daniel seven from three or four different trajectories by this point
but Daniel 10
Is less read we have touched on it before actually way back in one of the early episodes
But I won't guess which one because apparently I'm way off so
But in the before times. Yeah. So way back in the log ago time we briefly touched on it. But we're going to now go through it in some detail because this is one of the I wouldn't go so far as I did last time last time.
I mean, Daniel 7 really is for the sort of eschatological son of man figure is the Locust Classicus for discussing it, but Daniel 10 is not really the Locust Classicus for discussing the Heavenly Man, but
it's one of the most significant passages for this discussion.
So that's why we're starting there.
Right.
OK.
Well, I'm going to read the passage.
And this is, well, you'll hear this is Daniel speaking.
In the third year of Cyrus King of Persia,
a word was revealed to Daniel, who was named Belta Shazar,
and the word was true, and it was a great conflict.
And he understood the word and had understanding of the vision.
in those days I
Daniel was mourning for three weeks. I ate no pleasing food, no meat or wine entered my mouth,
nor did I anoint myself at all for the full three weeks. On the 24th day of the first month,
as I was standing on the bank of the Great River which is the Tigris. I lifted up my eyes and looked,
and there suddenly appeared a man clothed in linen with a belt of fine gold from Uphaz around
his waist. His body was like a barrel that's
B-E-R-Y-L, the gem. His body was like a barrel, his face like the appearance of lightning,
his eyes like flaming torches, his arms and legs like the gleam of burnished bronze,
and the sound of his words like the sound of a multitude. And only I, Daniel, saw the
vision. For the men who were with me did not see the vision, but a great trembling fell
upon them, and they fled to hide themselves. So I was left alone and saw this great vision,
no strength was left in me. My fair appearance was
changed and I retained no strength. Then I heard the sound of his words, and as I heard
the sound of his words, I fell on my face in deep sleep with my face to the ground, and
behold a hand touched me, and set me trembling on my hands and knees. And he said to me,
O Daniel, favored man in the Greek Old Testament, man of desires, understand the words that
I speak to you and stand upright for now I have been sent to you. And when he had spoken
this word.
me, I stood up trembling. Then he said to me,
"'Fear not, Daniel, for from the first day that you set your heart to understand and humbled
yourself before God, your words have been heard, and I have come because of your words.' The prince of
the kingdom of Persia withstood me twenty-one days, but Michael, one of the chief princes,
came to help me. For I was left there with the kings of Persia and came to make you understand
what has to happen to your people in the last days, for the vision is for days yet to come.
When he had spoken to me.
according to these words, I turned my face toward the ground and was mute, and immediately,
one having the likeness of the sons of Adam touched my lips.
Then I spoke my mouth, then I opened my mouth and spoke.
I said to he who stood before me, O my Lord, by reason of the vision, pains have come upon
me, and I retain no strength.
How can my Lord servant talk with my Lord, for now no strength remains in me, and no
breath was up to me?
Again, one having the appearance of a man touched me.
strengthened me, and he said, O favored man, again man of desires, fear not, peace be with
you, be strong and courageous. And as he spoke to me, I was strengthened and said, let my
Lord speak for you have strengthened me. Then he said, do you know why I have come to
you? But now I will return to fight against the Prince of Persia. And when I go out to be
hold, the Prince of Greece will come. But I will tell you what is inscribed in the book
of truth. There is none who contends by-
my side against these except Michael, your prince. So that's the vision.
Yes. And I'm making Father Andrew read these long passages because I have to save my voice for
nativity services. So I'm just that what it is throwing him right under the bus. So I'm a second
priest now. So you know, I don't really have anything I have to do. Yeah. So, uh,
and that's the whole of chapter 10 everybody by the way. Yeah, that's the whole chapter.
But
Yeah, and you may have noticed that as it was mentioned, it's in the first person and we briefly mentioned before
And we'll only touch on it briefly now, but the book of Daniels kind of a mess
textually textually. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. It switches between third person and first person
people are already at least a lot of people listening that's probably already aware that the Greek version is very different than the
we'll call it the other version because the other version, the older version, is part in Hebrew and part in
Aramaic and it switches back and forth at two points, one of which is exceedingly arbitrary that it just
all of a sudden switches to Aramaic. It starts out in Hebrew, switches to Aramaic at a seemingly
completely arbitrary point and then switches back to Hebrew for the last couple of chapters. And there
are like
a thousand theories because journal articles have to be published.
Disstrations have to be written.
Yeah, on why this is and how this is happening, there's a, there's a Dutch scholar who spent
his whole career like just writing about this issue.
Like, so, and the, the realizing, I mean, nobody knows for sure.
Yeah.
Exactly.
And what's going on and, and a lot of the theories are that these are different pieces
that came together later.
you know, that started out separate and et cetera, et cetera, et cetera.
But there are sort of through lines.
The reason I only reason I bring that up here is that as we're now going to be
talking about it and interpreting it, we are going to be interpreting it in the
context of the book of Daniel as a whole.
Right.
So we're taking for granted that this has some connections to what comes before
it at least.
We're not going to talk too much about what comes after it, but at least what comes
before it.
Um, yeah.
And yes, there are those folks, not just confined to 19th century Germany who would say,
you can't do that because it's written by eight different people, at least two of whom
were women.
But that's where we're going to go.
Because the reason for that, the justification for that, is that as Orthodox Christians,
the version of the text that has authority.
us. The version of the text that's important to us is the version of the text that is used
in red in the church. Right. So it doesn't matter what the historical process was that
God is there. It's that form of the text. Right. This is the one we've actually received.
Right. That's the one that has authority for us, not any hypothetical or even real earlier
versions. So all that said
We'll kind of go through and make some comments, you know, go back through what Father Andrew
just read sort of in Toto about this vision.
So you commented as you were going through on the Man of Desires thing.
Yeah, right.
Which if folks have been going to Liturgy the last couple of weeks, they've probably heard
that title a few times.
And man of desires is...
really vague, in English.
Yeah, and even like the explanations that I've read for it,
like, for instance, I copied out the one that's from,
this is from the cynic sodium,
that's in the great Hologian, the Greek tradition one.
And it says this about this,
Daniel, whose name means God is judge,
in case everybody was wondering,
was called Man of Desires by the Angels that appeared
because he courageously disdained every desire of the body,
even the very bread that is necessary for nourishment,
which that seems like opposite of what it means.
Like man of desires would seem to mean,
a man who has a lot of desires,
but this is actually about him denying those desires.
And then it says furthermore,
he received this name because in his longing
for the freedom of those of his tribe
and his desire to know their future condition,
he ceased not supplicating God,
fasting and bending the knee three times a day,
which that's a little bit more,
makes all that
more sense with the idea of him being a man of desires. But that's not quite what it means,
right? And either what is it? Airmanck or Hebrew here?
Well, airmanck or Greek depending on which version you're reading.
But yeah, and this, the contrast you're pointing out in that surface reading of the Sinek
and English is even more pronounced in Greek because the word
that's translated desire in the Greek version of this is a form of epithemia, which is epithemia is what's used for like passions.
Yeah. Right.
Like desires in that sense. Right.
And so then it's saying he's called the man of desires because of his asceticism and you're like what?
Yeah, right right right so what's going on is
actually not sort of a weird opposite contradiction, but a kind of wordplay. Right. Because whenever you see,
this is a general tip. When you see it in English translation, an English biblical translation of
Greek, when you see of, right, that's like that's a punt. Right. Because what that means is you have a
word that's in the genitive. And the Greek genitive can be used in lots of different ways.
right. But when you have a committee translating something, all those people in that committee
disagree about which way you should translate it in this particular instance. And so you
end up just, well, we'll just put off. Okay. Is everybody, right? Like is everybody happy
with that? Right. So that should tell you that there's some, anytime you see an off like
that, like man of desires, you know, there's some further interpretation that needs to take
place that hasn't yet, right?
Right.
It's a good marker.
So the idea behind both the air man here and the way the Greek is used is not that this is a man who
possesses desires or who is filled with desires or passions, but this is a man who is pleasing or who
is desired. Yeah, it's a desirable man. Right. Sort of the idea. Or a man who is favored, right? That kind
of that kind of a deep.
pleasing our favorite man, right? And so the idea that's going on sort of behind the English of the the Sinek
Sari and is the idea that, right, this play that Daniel cut off the pleasures of this world and became pleasing to God.
By these means and and there's a fun sort of wordplay where it talks about.
He eats no pleasing food when he's talking about his asceticism.
there in the scripture or no Daniel 10.
What's translated there is I ate no pleasing food, no meat or wine entered my mouth.
The word pleasing there is the same word.
So this wasn't food that had lots of passions and desires.
The food was just laying there.
That's a different episode.
That's an episode of empty tails or something.
I was going to say it was a reference to cannibalism maybe.
It's always...
werewolves with you. Anyway. So right, so it's this it's this kind of idea that in the way that like
meat and wine, right, would be the pleasing food, the desirable food, right, he made himself pleasing
to God by cutting off those things that would please him. Pleasing food. Yeah. Right. Right. So
that's the that's the that's what the cynics are in is doing. That's what's going on with this man of
of desires title.
Gotcha.
Uh, that we hear, hear over and over again.
And so, relatedly as we just talked about, right, notice that Daniel here is trying to
receive this vision, he's seeking wisdom from God, right, this kind of prophetic wisdom.
And in order to do that, he's practicing asceticism, right?
This is not just this Christian innovation.
This is not something that comes from Platonism or Nosticism or something, right?
This is Jewish man living at exile.
practicing a cynicism, and even the way he fasts will be kind of familiar to Orthodox Christians,
because it's not that he just doesn't eat anything. Right. Right. It's that he cuts out certain
pleasing foods. In this case meat and alcohol. Yeah. Right. It doesn't eat certain kinds of things.
Right. The most pleasing things. Right. He goes for a simpler, sparer diet, right, in order to focus
on prayer.
order to seek this wisdom from God, and then that prayer is answered. And so the way in which
that prayer is answered is that this man appears to him. Right? He lives by the river, he's by the
Tigris River, and he looks up and there's a man there, but even though he's identified at first as a
the man, the description.
right? His clothes is okay, right? That that he's got, you know, a linen, linen garment and a gold sash, right?
But then his faces like lightning his arms and legs are like, you know, burnish bronze, right? So
So it's not saying, it gems in metal and yeah, yeah, yeah, this is a describing like a
Docs avid
or anything. This is. Wow. See, that was when I got. Thank you. Thank you. Man of bronze.
Yes. Anyway, uh, Doc Savage. Yes. So, um, but it's also clearly not your run of the mill human,
right? It's not just, oh, he looked up at another another prophet came to walk in.
he's he's definitely deeply weird and sort of spectacular looking you know right right yeah yeah and
There is another place in the Bible where someone else has a vision and sees a very similar
Looking man. Where could it be father Stephen? That's in the book of Revelation
Right, so Revelation chapter one
verses 12 through 15
This is the Apostle John now speaking then I turned to see the voice that was speaking to me and on turning
I saw seven golden lamp stands and in the midst of the lamp stands one...
like a son of man clothed with a long robe and with a golden sash around his chest. The hairs of
his head were white like white wool like snow. His eyes were like a flame of fire. His feet were like
burnished bronze refined in a furnace and his voice was like the roar of many waters.
Right. And so maybe notice that's that's similar but not quite the same. Right. And
And this is one of these interesting little
think this is a rabbit trail we won't go all the way down.
I was thinking about it. Yeah, we'll tip our toes in the Tigers River.
And so the, the, this is not, St John is not here in Revelation chapter one,
sort of just referencing the Greek of Daniel 10. Yeah, it's not a quote.
Right he seems to be because there are sort of weird
differences between the Greek and the Aramaic of Daniel 10. He seems to be citing the Aramaic
in Greek. Translation. Right. His own translation from Aramaic into Greek. And that's why things
sound really similar, but they're not sort of identical because when you, you know, if you're
translating directly from Aramaic into English, and then from Aramaic to Greek to English,
the English you get out of those two processes is a good amount.
Exactly. Right. Right. But that's what's going on here. And that, by the way, strongly
implies that whoever wrote the book of Revelation was a first language, Aramaic speaker,
yeah, like somebody from Galilee. I'll just leave that there. But so, yeah, so this is
And this isn't right.
Let's be clear, Saint John is likewise having a vision.
Right.
In the same way that reading Daniel, right, and sort of doing a remix, right?
Yeah.
It's, it's that he's having a vision and he's seeing something very similar to what Daniel is
seeing.
But because, of course, he's steeped in the Daniel tradition.
When he goes to write it down, he's putting it in similar terms, you know,
and seems to be trained.
insulating on some level, but it's not, you know, again, it's not, it's not just him quoting,
right? He's actually having a vision. And I think, you know, just as a side note, just
like you said, the version of these books that we receive are the, as canonical are the
versions that we receive. We also have to receive them as having integrity of their own
and not just say, well, I don't think he really had a vision because he says I had a vision.
You know, it's like, well, if you're just going to say you're a liar.
than why are we bothering to read this book? But you know, I don't know. Not a liar.
So the question then and the fact that we've brought up the apocalypse of St. John probably
gives away the answer we're going to come up with by making this connection that we just made.
but the question that is who is who is this man who is this man who is this man
statue
same time. Yeah. Yeah. Who Daniel sees. I will throw in one little. I'm definitely not
going following this out, but just for for those of you who might want another little piece,
another little data point in terms of St. Paul receiving a prophetic call on the road to Damascus,
rather than being a quote unquote convert.
Notice what Daniel says right after he describes the man he saw. He says,
only I Daniel saw the vision for the men who are with me did not see the vision,
but a great trembling fell upon them. Compare that to how St. Paul narrates what happened to the men,
the other men who are with him on the road to Damascus. Yeah, pretty much the same. And I mean,
there's stuff that just happens in various places like where Christ speaks to the voice of the
voice the Father speaks to him.
And of course, you know, John writes it down what he said and I says, but some said it thundered.
Like this is a thing that you that happens every so often. Yeah. Yeah.
So that little tidbit being thrown out there, that's the that's the the the cheap present that goes in your stocking, I guess, before you get the real presence that we're going to get into now.
The
In terms of who this is, we've got some candidates sort of in the context.
There are some angelic beings, some divine beings who we've already seen in Daniel and who
we've seen in the immediate context.
So one candidate might be St. Michael, the archangel, right?
And of course, we can kind of rule him out right off the bat because twice here in this
the man who were identifying
refers to Saint Michael and the third person.
Yeah, so that wouldn't work.
For someone who is with him and someone who is on his side,
so it can't be him.
So next candidate might be the Archangel Gabriel,
after whom my parish is named.
Right?
And those two are put in context
and Saint Gabriel does appear in Daniel,
but here's the problem.
He just appeared in Daniel.
Right. So if he was mentioning him again, it would just say and Gabriel came to me again, you know or something like that
Right, he wouldn't give this description and fall on his face and right have this extreme reaction to seeing somebody who he just saw twice
Plus plus when you know
When Gabriel's mentioned in Daniel 816
Daniel says this and I heard a man's voice between the banks of the Ulye the river and it called
Gabriel make
this man understand the vision. So there's the voice, this man's voice who is giving Gabriel orders.
You know, uh, right. So that voice is coming from the river by which Daniel now sees this man.
Right. That's the beginning of chapter 10. Right. And so it makes sense that if we're reading this
through that we would say, Oh, this man who he now sees must be the man who was talking to Gabriel
in 816. Yeah exactly. Right. Now he's.
him at the river. So that rules out the two of them, but we also get this other clue in terms of the
context of Daniel, and that's that there are actually three descriptions of this man in chapter 10
that you read, not just the one. The one is the most detailed, but then twice after that he's
described, right? And in the other two, the first one is that
He's one having the likeness of the sons of Adam.
And in Greek it has one having the likeness of a son of man.
Son of man, yep.
Right, which I mean, those are commensurate, right?
Because Adam is the word for man.
Right.
See, we talked about last episode.
Yeah.
See the, see the tortuous winding road of our last episode.
And then after that, he is again referred to, right?
Again, what having the appearance of a man?
Yep, right.
So, this man appears both in this kind of heavenly fashion, right?
This, that we also see paralleled in Revelation, and that, and that as we go forward tonight,
we'll see paralleled other places as well.
But he also appears just as someone who looks like a human, right?
Which is what we saw on Daniel 7 last time.
Right, so you've got both
this spectacular divine appearance, and then he also looks like a man.
Right.
You know, so it's a heavenly appearance, and it's a human appearance.
And when Saint John sees the same man with the same description, it is the appearance of the heavenly
Christ.
Right.
Bumst St. John had also seen.
As a man.
Right.
Yep.
So you've got his gospel showing him as a man and sometimes as God.
Although he is clear, he is both the whole time.
Let me just clarify that.
Yes.
And then of course he's also in then revelation much more of a divine appearance.
But again he is also man in revelation.
There's just these different emphases between the two accounts.
Right.
Yep.
come to the king.
then, or at least we posit the hypothesis, that this is Christ, right? This is the second
person of the Holy Trinity. This is God the Son, right? Who Daniel is talking to you? That
raises questions about the end of the chapter that we read, right?
Yeah, there's all this stuff about him battling the Prince of Persia and St. Michael coming
to give him a hand.
And no one but Michael coming to give him a hand.
Right. No one but Michael being on a side and you would say, well, if this is God the son, if this is the second person of the Trinity,
number one, why would he need an angel's help?
Right. Isn't he just God and number two, why can't he just, you know,
curb stomp this demon and move on?
Why is there why is there even a battle going on? Right?
And so we have to take this within the context of not just Daniel,
but of the Old Testament as a whole.
sort of where we are in sort of the movement and sweep of the entire Old Testament. Right. Right.
So, you know, thinking back now to the first of this series of four episodes where we talked about
the Angel of the Lord, there's a bunch of times where the Angel of the Lord not only appears and
talks to someone but actually fights in battles and you know fights alongside
and leads the armies of Israel, right? So you've got this image already exists as a warrior image.
It's already a thing, you know, in scripture, yeah. Right, and that place, right, that the central
place where that occurs is in the Torah at the time of the Exodus. Right. Right. A bunch of spots
around there right yeah yeah like when it says that God is a man of war available now it's stored
Sorry. I'm going to put that one up there.
Thanks. Good book everybody. Good book everybody.
So, um,
but, um, so that happens around the Exodus.
So, as we've talked about on the show before,
what's happening at the Exodus? Right.
So, the nations, right, God has,
because of his holiness,
because he doesn't want to destroy human kind of,
after the flood has...
with drawn from the world has placed these angelic beings
over the nations.
Those angelic beings have rebelled.
And as we hear here in Daniel 10,
St. Michael's the only one who stayed loyal,
who is the sort of patron in guardian angel of Israel itself.
Yeah.
But so at the time of the Exodus,
The people of Israel are in Egypt.
and they're enslaved in Egypt, and that's not just physical slavery, right?
That's included, but that's also spiritual slavery, because remember, at the time of the
Passover, God says he's going to render judgment against the gods of Egypt.
Right. Not just against Pharaoh and his crew, right.
Right. And so they have to be delivered from those, those spiritual enemies and then brought
to the land. So by the time we get to Daniel, Daniel is living in the Babylonian exile.
Yeah, right so the people in their disobedience
Right have suffered the people of Judah have suffered the curses of the covenant. They've gone back into exile the Exodus has been undone
They're they're now again living in a foreign land under a foreign oppressor
Including their gods under these foreign gods right the Prince of Persia
Right and pretty soon the Prince of Greece is going to come through right and
And
And they're back in this situation.
And so this is why when you read the exilic prophets,
including Daniel, the hope is that there's going to be
this new exodus that's going to end the exile.
Right.
And bring them back.
And if there's going to be a new exile and they're going
to be brought back, then that means once again,
the angel of Yahweh, the Yahweh angel, right?
Who is Yahweh himself is going to need to come
and leave them in the battle to defeat.
and battle against Israel's enemies, right?
Judas enemies.
And so what this is saying, what this is saying,
what's being talked about here by the heavenly man
when he talks to Daniel about this battle he's engaged in
with the Prince of Persia and then the Prince of Greece,
is that that salvation, that new Exodus,
that new Passover, that new Pentecost that are coming
is already in motion.
We're in media race right now, right?
so the God
is in process. Right? Yeah, right. And like one of the things that's said in the vision where
where God speaks to Daniels, he says that this is about, I can't remember exactly where it is,
but he says this is about the future. This is things to come. Right? So there's there's this sense of
it's it's not just talking, you know, it's not talking about the Exodus from Egypt for instance,
but it's also not just talking about presumably return from Babylonian.
exile, but as we talked about last time in particular, this is way bigger than all of that.
Right. Yeah. Yeah. Right. This is the big defeat of all the false gods because it's not
enough. Right. This is why there's a promise of a new covenant. Right. Yeah. Because just
re-initiating the old covenant would have just been restarting this whole cycle anew. Right.
where Israel sins again.
and goes back into exile, right?
Just like you see that cycle play out a dozen times
in the book of judges, right?
That's not enough, right?
So this is why it's fulfillment.
It's filled to overflowing, right?
This time, it's a new covenant.
It's an everlasting covenant, right?
It's going to not just manage sin,
but it's going to deal with sin once for all.
It's not going to just manage death.
It's going to do away with death, right?
And so this, yeah.
which then is
explains a lot of the language in Daniel 7 about this kingdom having no end.
Right. Right. And, and this is in motion. And we're not going to go through all of these chapters of Daniel,
but this is the context in which the time when Christ's birth is going to be as predicted,
pretty close to to the year.
So this process is in motion, right?
We talked about how...
I'll show how the word gospel is talking about is the report of a victory, right?
Christ's victory.
And we talked last time with the Son of Man.
There's this victory that's won over these demonic powers after which Christ is enthroned
and all power and heaven on earth has been given to him.
Well, what we'll just say at what Christ is saying here to Daniel is that the opening skirmishes
of that great battle.
beginning of that second greater fulfilled exes is now in motion. And that's going to culminate
then in the victory of Christ that we see unfold in the gospels. Yeah, because he's taking on directly
these principalities that are over these pagan nations, the prince of Persia, the prince of Greece.
Yeah. Yes, they're being dealt with.
right so yeah so I mean these these prophecy
in Daniel are related ultimately then to this eschatological victory, which is why then
you see this stuff appearing again in St. John's Apocalypse at the end of the New Testament,
because this is about the culmination of all things. This is about the great victory of Christ
over his enemies. Right. So, all right, well, that is the first...
of tonight's episode of The Lord of Spirits,
and we're gonna take a short break,
and we'll be right back with the second half.
Father Andrew Stephen Damick
and Father Stephen DeYoung
will be back in a moment
to take your calls on the next part
of The Lord of Spirits.
Give them a call at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF Radio.
Are you curious about the Orthodox Christian faith?
Do you have questions about Orthodox Christianity that you can't trust strangers and internet
forums to answer?
Are you an Orthodox Christian looking for a reliable first place to send your interested
friends?
Do you need help finding an Orthodox church near you?
My name is Father Paul Hodge.
I serve in the Antiochian Orthodox Christian Archdiocese of North America.
My name is Father Joseph Lucas.
Bye.
in the Orthodox Church in America.
My name is Father Anthony Cook.
I serve in the Greek Orthodox Archdiocese of America.
And I'm Father Andrew Stephen Damick,
Chief Content Officer of Ancient Faith Ministries
and a priest of the Antioch in Archdiocese.
And we're the Orthodox Intro Team.
If you're looking for a first stop online
to getting's introduction to the Orthodox faith,
a place to get answers to questions
from qualified Orthodox Christian clergy,
a place to send your friends and not...
just toss them into the chaos of the internet.
A place to get help finding an Orthodox parish
and get plugged into an actual Orthodox community,
then point your web browser at orthroxintro.org.
Orthodoxintro.org is a free service of ancient faith ministries
and made possible by our donors.
It's an Orthodox on ramp to the Christian life.
Again, that's orthroxintro.org.
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits, the Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father
Stephen DeYoung.
If you have a question, call now at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF radio.
Welcome back.
This is a second half of the show and it's where we begin to take your calls.
So give us a ring we'd like to hear from you, just like the voice of...
Steve said 855 AF radio or 855 237 2346.
So we just took a little romp through Daniel chapter 10,
pretty much the whole chapter.
And we've got a whole lot more now to look at.
This episode, we're gonna just be looking
at a whole bunch of scriptural passages.
So strap in everybody.
Yeah.
But if you tune into this show
and you're not interested in the Bible,
I'm kind of not sure why.
Right?
What are you doing here?
here. Yeah. Right.
To the wrong place. Yeah. Exactly. Exactly.
So, all right. Well, okay. So what's what's the first thing
that we're going to look at here? Another one of the prophets?
Yes. We're actually going to be looking at several more of the
prophets here. But yeah, this is where you know, as as we said,
you know, nobody ever sees God and lives except for when they do.
And so we're going to go through some times.
when they do. Yeah and the point okay so we're not like trying to contradict that line from the
scriptures. You know that is a line from the scriptures and this actually came up in a lot of
questions we got especially after our last episode. People were like well you know maybe no one really
does see God but but but the point is is that when the scripture says that you can't see God
It doesn't, it's not creating an absolute rule that always applies in...
every possible way. It's referring to a certain way, you know, that in which you don't see God,
because then you've also got not only as we've been we're talking about appearances of God,
where people were instances where people do see God, but then you even have direct addresses
of it like where, you know, the Lord says, bless out of the pure and hard for they shall see God.
Right? So I mean, he actually addresses it outright. So we can't say, well, these are places
is where people aren't re-
see in God because Christ says you can see God. Right. So obviously when the scripture says these
things, it's talking about different things. It's not exactly the same thing being addressed here,
but more on that later, right? Right. So, right. Yeah. So we're not, we're not, nobody can see God
and live except when they do is not saying that that first statement is it true. It's trying to
deal with what we actually have in the scriptures. So it exit is 33 where God says
no one can see my face and live just a few verses earlier in the same chapter.
It says that he spoke to Moses face to face.
Right.
That's not an editing error.
So that's that's there.
So we have to add a big part of what we're doing, not just in this episode,
but in all four of these episodes about Christ to the Old Testament is explaining how that works
because the revelation of Christ that becomes clear
in the New Testament is what explains all this, right? Right? It's what makes all this
makes sense. If you didn't have it, right, the Hebrew Bible by itself, there's lots of
things that don't make sense. Yeah. And that's why when you get into rabbinical Judaism, right,
when you study rabbinical Judaism, you look at just like the Talmud, what you find are
or dozens of different rabbis, all of whom are...
are incredibly revered who all have radically different opinions in different ways of solving
all these problems in the Hebrew Scriptures.
Yeah.
And it's just a constant conversation and debate because there's no single through line
and resolution, right?
Yeah.
So Christianity, unless you have Christ, right, right.
Christianity has a through line that connects all this and explains all this.
Yeah.
Now, if you ask, I was going to say to be fair to orthodox Jewish friends, they would say
That's not a bug.
gets a feature of their religion, that it's a constant discussion and debate and framing.
Sure. Okay. Right. We would, I would say, right, that clarity, right, because the Holy
Spirit is a Spirit of Order and not confusion, as St. Paul reminds us, that clarity that comes
through Christ, it'd be able to understand the scriptures is a superior benefit. But that's
That's why I'm a Christian and not an Orthodox Jew.
It part.
Right, right.
Okay. So all right. Well, so we've got something from Jeremiah chapter one, which we're not,
I'm not going to read that whole chapter to you. We're just going to mention the bits that are
relevant to what we're talking about. I mean, you could. I could. I mean, it's actually kind of
do whatever we want, but it's okay. Yeah. We're making you read enough. Yeah. So yeah. So yeah,
Jeremiah chapter one is one might expect in the first chapter is talking about Jeremiah's
call to be a profit. Right. And in it going back.
to our episode about the Word of the Lord, the Dabariya Wea. There's this interesting back and forth
where it literally alternates back and forth between the Word of the Lord, Dabariya Wea,
talking to Jeremiah and just Yahweh talking to Jeremiah. Right? And it's not presented as there are
these two different people standing in front of Jeremiah.
It's percent it is.
is what the word of Yahweh is also Yahweh.
But one of the interesting parts of this is that at one point in particular, in verse
9, at this one point in particular, this figure is described in physical terms, in terms of
having a at least a couple of body parts.
The figure who's described as having these body parts is not the word of the Lord, but just the Lord just y'all learn
Yeah, yeah, like in verse nine it says
Then the Lord and that's Lord and all cap so then Yahweh put out his hand and put out his hand and touched my mouth
Right and so
Because of the language, right? This is really hard to take feet.
here deeply. Right. I can't touch it. You can say, Oh, the hand of the Lord was upon him.
Oh, well, that's metaphorical. Right. That's there. But this is literally he reached out
his hand and touched my mouth. There's not really a good metaphorical way to take that.
Right. It's describing the extension of the arm. Right. So there is a figure who is Yahweh
who has at least an arm in a hand standing in front of Jeremiah. Right. And this and
This is inv-
in his prophetic call. Right. Yeah.
So okay, well, the next passage we're gonna look at is Ezekiel chapter one.
Yes, yes. The whole chapter. The whole chapter. And I mean, you know, I'm not gonna
apologize because you have to kind of take in all this together. Yes. It's so easy.
So many times, you know, like Christians we read a verse or two, which can be okay,
but if you don't read it all together or hear it all together
sometimes you're gonna get it wrong then or kind of off or distorted when you
try to understand what it's saying okay so this is the chapter oh go ahead go
ahead here at Lord of Spirits we have a 100-year tradition of addressing a certain
topic every every Christmas that's right and it's gonna be addressed at this
passage exactly so yeah all right okay so Ezekiel chapter one in the
30th year in
the fourth month on the fifth day of the month, as I was among the exiles by the Hebar
Canal, the heavens were opened, and I saw visions of God. On the fifth day of the month,
it was the fifth year of the exile of King Jehoekin. The word of the Lord came to Ezekiel,
the priest, the son of Boosey and the land of the Caldians by the Hebar Canal, and the
hand of the Lord was upon him there. As I looked behold, a stormy wind came out of the
North and a great cloud with...
brightness around it, and fire flashing forth continually and in the midst of the fire as
it were gleaming metal, and from the midst of it came the likeness of four living creatures,
and this was their appearance. They had a human likeness, but each had four faces, and
each of them had four wings. Their legs were straight, and the soles of their feet were
like the sole of a calf's foot, and they sparkled like burnished bronze. Under their wings
on their four sides they had human hands.
hands, and the four had their faces and their wings thus, their wings touched one another.
Each one of them went straight forward without turning as they went.
As for the likeness of their faces, each had a human face.
The four had the face of a lion on the right side, the four had the face of an ox on the
left side, and the four had the face of an eagle.
Such were their faces, and their wings were spread out above.
creature had two wings, each of which touched the wing of another.
two covered their bodies, and each went straight forward. Wherever the spirit would go, they
went without turning as they went. As the likeness of the living creatures, their appearance
was like burning coals of fire, like the appearance of torches moving to and fro among living
creatures, and the fire was bright and out of the fire went forth lightning, and the living
creatures darted to and fro like the appearance of a flash of lightning. Now, as I looked at
living creatures I saw a wheel on the earth beside the living creatures.
one for each of the four of them.
As for the appearance of the wheels and their construction,
their appearance was like the gleaming of barrel,
and the four had the same likeness,
their appearance and construction being as it were a wheel within a wheel,
when they went, they went in any of their four directions
without turning as they went.
And their rims were tall and awesome,
and the rims of all four were full of eyes all around.
And when the living creatures went, the wheels went beside them
and when the living creatures
rose from the earth, the wheels rose. Wherever the Spirit wanted to go, they went, and
the wheels rose along with them, for the Spirit of the living creatures was in the wheels.
When those went, these went, and when those stood, these stood, and when those rose from
the earth, the wheels rose along with them, for the Spirit of the living creatures was
in the wheels. Over the heads of the living creatures, there was the likeness of an expanse,
shining like awe, inspiring crystal, spread out above their heads, and under the expanse
there
wings were stretched out straight one toward another, and each creature had two wings covering
its body, and when they went I heard the sound of their wings like the sound of many waters,
like the sound of the Almighty, a sound of tumult like the sound of an army. When they stood
still they let down their wings, and there came a voice from above the expanse over their
heads, when they stood still they let down their wings. And above the expanse, over their
heads that was the likeness of a throne, in appearance like soft...
fire, and seated above the likeness of a throne, was a likeness with a human appearance.
And upward from what had the appearance of his waist, I saw as it were gleaming metal,
like the appearance of fire and closed all around.
And downward from what had the appearance of his waist, I saw as it were the appearance
of fire and there was brightness around him.
Like the appearance of the bow that is in the cloud on the day of rain, so was the appearance
of the brightness, all of...
around such was the appearance of the likeness of the glory of the Lord.
And when I saw it, I fell on my face and I heard the voice of one speaking.
Wow.
Wheels in the sky keep on turning.
Thank you so much for making references that I get.
I try once a while.
I thank you.
Yes.
Of course, some of us would pass you so you don't even realize you didn't get them.
It's not occasion.
So I'm okay with that too.
Yeah.
Bunch of
There are no references I will get, especially with songs like that.
So yeah, so you got, I mean, okay, you got these four living creatures.
What's going on with that?
And then especially if you are familiar with this podcast, and this is not your first episode,
when you see wheels with eyes, you know that's the throne of God.
Yes.
Right.
kind of gives us a sense of where we're looking at.
Not so.
definitely not aliens. Yeah. Right. So this is part of, we've talked a lot about thrown
chariot stuff, Mirkava stuff on on this podcast. So people are familiar with the idea of the
thrown chariot. This is particularly emphasized with Ezekiel because remember Ezekiel like
Daniel is an exile. He's a profit of the exile. And so, uh...
Ezekiel literally sees the throne of God, the throne chariot of God, leave the temple
before it's destroyed. And the idea here is that God's throne is sort of mobile. And
therefore can encompass the whole of the earth. So he's not like a local territorial god of that
strip of land. And he's not just the god of a particular people. He is the god.
He is he has got to the universe and this whole description in ways
Some more subtle than others shall we say or some more difficult to understand for modern readers than others is
Is aimed at giving that impression that he is the cosmic universal
Most high God the God of gods. Yeah, there's the rainbow and you know, he's above the sky and all that kind of stuff right and
so
part of what's going on here
that we would be remiss not to mention given that we we have to talk about astrology in our Christmas episode every year.
It's a rule. It's a tradition.
Terribim Zodiac.
Yes, here comes the chair of Imzodiac as promised.
Yes.
So we have these four living creatures.
So the picture, in the case people tried to picture this in their heads, right?
is that you have these four cherubim.
these four living creatures. That's what Caravim means is living creatures, right? And picture your
Babylonian
Sphinx-like things, right? Yeah, the Lamassu. Go go go go go you can see yeah. Yeah, yeah, right. So
and they there are four of them facing in the four directions. Each of them has four faces,
right? The face of the four directions also. But their wings are touching,
right so that they're sort of in a circle flying in a circle right
facing out from each other with their wings touching and with their wings making a platform
on which is this blue firmament that is the sky and then the chariot throne of God is on top of that.
Right, sort of above the heavens, right? So then what are these cherubim about? Well,
the clue here if you're a nerd is that
is the four faces. Right, the four faces of the four living creatures. Right, there's a human
face, a lion face, an ox face, and an eagle face. Right. And so what you need to imagine is that
the Babylonians, like all of these other ancient cultures, had a zodiac. Right, they had a set of
12 constellations, right?
that they used to track the seasons and the times in the sky.
And so within those 12, there were four cardinal zodiac signs,
representing the cardinal directions in the sky,
that you would orient yourself by in the sky.
And in the Babylonian astrology, those four cardinal signs
were...
a man, a lion, an ox, and an eagle.
How about that?
So, these cherubim, these angelic spirits, are also constellations.
Yeah.
And that's why it could talk about the spirits of the constellations being also in the wheels.
to move to move them about right.
So these are those four constellations. And so this, this is something that St.
Irenaeus still knew about. Yeah, he picks up on this. Yeah, because there's this famous
passage that not a lot of people have read in Toto in context, but that a lot of people are
sort of vaguely familiar with.
Which is that same...
Nirenias is the earliest Christian author we know of who talks about these four creatures,
right? These four faces as being connected to the four gospels. Right? And that's something
that gets picked up by a lot of later fathers. But what you'll find when you compare the
different fathers is they tend to match up different faces with different gospels.
Huh, right.
And the reason for that is
That's not the basis of the connection.
What I mean by that is they did not read those lists
of faces and say, hey, this sounds like the four gospels.
That's not how they got there.
Yeah.
Right? They got there a different way.
And this is that way.
If you read the text from St. Aaron Ace
where he talks about this, he doesn't just say,
hey, there are these four living creatures
and hey, they represent the four gospels.
Though I-
once I'll Rod Parsley talk about this at Saint
Irenaeus.
I've had this run.
Parsley has run.
Parsley ever.
I was dumbfounded.
I guess a book fell off the shelf and landed open.
I don't know.
I'm currently dumbfounded.
That was the last meme I thought you would make.
Yes.
So but wow.
So that's not the ability to get.
If you read that whole section, Saint
Irenaeus talks about how not just the four living creatures,
but also
there are four wins, there are four corners of the earth.
Yeah.
Right.
There are four cardinal compass directions.
So, and again, he's not just saying like,
hey, here's a bunch of stuff that there's four of.
Right.
But all of those examples, the four wins,
the four cardinal directions, these four constellations.
Right.
The four quarters of the earth.
All of those things represent, again,
just what they represent here in Ezekiel.
this idea of truth.
of the whole cosmos, right, of the whole world, right, of wholeness and completion by having the four, right, together.
And it's from there that Saint Irenaeus goes to.
And therefore, this is why it is appropriate and fitting that we have four gospels.
Now does he identify a particular face with each gospel or?
He does, but he does that sort of last.
Right.
And so the later fathers who
pick up on him, all agree with his basic point, but then match them up differently.
Interesting. Right. Yeah. Cause I know that in like iconography, especially like manuscript
iconography in the West, it gets pretty consistent where you get the man is Matthew, the
eagle is John, the ox is Luke, and then the lion is Mark, perhaps most famously depicted
at least for those of us here in the West
in the Book of Kells, where they've got that in...
incredible illumination page that has all four,
or you know, that, actually,
I don't think it's one page that has all four.
Oh, there it might be.
But anyways, it's in there.
And then I think it's the,
in the Lindisfarne Gospel as well.
But I mean, it's all over the place.
You get, you get those images
lined up in exactly that way
in a lot of iconography.
Right.
And I believe, and someone can,
I'm actually me on this because, as is well known,
once you get to the fourth century AD,
I lose all interest in the world.
But I believe
that that codification is found in St. Gregor, the deologist.
St. Gregor is great.
That particular matchup.
And so I find it likely that they're following that.
Yeah, yeah.
And I just looked it up.
Obviously, I just looked it up by the way.
There is indeed a single page in the book of Kells
that has all four of them together.
So which is really cool, by the way.
You just Google up a book of Kells, K-E-L-L-S,
gospel animals, and you'll see the picture I'm talking about.
It's pretty neat, everybody.
Yeah.
Cool.
There's also a whole doctor who audio adventure where they try to steal the book of Kells,
but that's less interesting in that statement.
I just thought I'd throw it in.
How dare they?
Yeah, no, I've seen it.
I mean, 20 years ago, I went to the UK and I was on pilgrimage and I went to Dublin and
at Trinity College, Dublin, they have the book of Kells there and you can go into this dark
room and they'll have a couple of pages from a couple of the different volumes opened
up and you can actually see it there.
I mean, it's, you know, it...
It's a holy book, like it has its own kind of holy presence to it, which you can definitely
sense when you go in there.
So yeah, I mean, this stuff plays out.
It's not just written in a prophecy somewhere, but this stuff plays out in terms of the real
depth of Christian culture.
Yeah.
This is a pretty firmly, yeah.
Ingrain thing.
Yeah, but the key is that.
So this.
This is, I'm going to go ahead and pause to make this general point.
The way a lot of folks tend to use the church fathers and the scriptures is that the ancient
Christian commentary on scriptures has done us no favors in this regard, is that people
tend to, like, I don't understand this verse or this passage.
I will go look up in something like the AC.
I will go and look up what church fathers say about it.
If they all seem to say basically the same thing,
then I'll just sort of proof text it and say,
well, that's what it means.
And if they disagree, then those are like options.
And I can choose which one of these I want to hold, right?
All of which is bad.
And abuse of the church fathers, right?
right? So
Something like the ACCS could be useful if you use it as like an index, like if you use it to say,
Hey, here's where I could go look to see St. John Chrysostom talk about this passage, for example, right?
But what's more important than reading an English translation of what a church father said in a particular
homily or a particular theological work with reference to that verse is
figuring out why
Right, yeah, is understanding how...
how that father got there, right?
Because a lot of times if you just look up
what church fathers say about a text,
you'll be holding the book sideways,
trying to figure out what does that have to do.
Right.
Why is he talking about this?
There's a great example.
We talked about Daniel 10 in the first half of the show.
Go look at patricistic commentaries on the description
of the heavenly man in Daniel 10.
And you'll find this incredible amount of
of ink spilled on Tarsish. Okay. Where was Tarsish? Exactly. In the air of the air, it's
not. Well, it's sort of is. It talks about gold that came from a particular place, which
is another name for Tarsish, right? In the Greek, it doesn't say gold from Tarsish. It just
says he wore a sash of Tarsish.
Ha.
Right. So the church fathers all eventually arrive at, well, it's gold.
They all arrive at the same place as our translation. Right. But because they're looking at this
sort of odd Greek translation, they have to spill a lot of ink to explain, well, they got gold from
Tarshish and etc. It's all to come back to. It's a gold sash. Yeah. Right. But so if you just go and
and look at that proof text and say, oh, well, this...
is a man from Tarsish or something, like you're going to be way off.
Right. Right. Yeah.
You have to find out what are they looking at?
What are they seeing? What are they doing?
Why are they applying it this way? Right? How?
What is their understanding? Right?
So if you, if you just look in this case at St.
Ear and Aston say, well, St.
Ear and A. It says those four faces represent the four
possible. Right. Right. Meaning that's what was being communicated
to a Zekial. A Zekial was supposed to see this vision.
And think at some point 500 years from now.
Right, 600 years from now, a group of four disciples of the Messiah will write the story
of his victory over the powers of death in Hades.
And each of them will have a character similar to one of these faces.
Right?
Obviously that's not it.
Right.
There's way more going on here.
And so just from reading the chapter, you can see that.
Right.
We have to delve into the original text and then see what St. Earnay has said about it and
and then figure out
how he got there. And then this all kind of unfolds. Right? This all kind of unfolds in front
of us. Right? And we can get much more out of both the Bible and the church fathers.
So end rant on that. All right. But I get to do that once in a while, I guess. Yeah. I mean,
we're live. We're on live. Who could stop the? So we could cut my mic, I guess, but truly
would never do that to you. She's sorely tempted all the time.
Yeah, never actually pulls the trigger.
Okay, so too.
So Zodiac.
So that covers we had to talk about the chair of a Zodiac for Christmas.
We had to get some astrology in here.
No, I'm not going to, I'm not going to, I'll save it for next Christmas.
Okay.
So last Christmas you gave me, no, you gave me your heart.
Very next day.
I gave it away. Oh, yeah.
Yeah.
So
I've tried to work at it all I want for Christmas is you reference and it's not coming to me.
But I guess I just did.
Thank you anyway.
Thank you very much.
Yeah.
Okay.
So there's another.
Yeah.
There's another.
Then there's another image we wanted to focus on and that's the one from versus 26 through
28, which is actually germane to our topic tonight.
So we're getting back from that torture is circle of locution back to.
Preambulation.
Back to the topic at hand.
Yes, and that is that what who is ultimately seen once we have the throne described and the sky and the constellations and the stars and the heavens and all of this described
then seated on the throne is the likeness of a human.
Yeah, it's interesting the way that the scene unfolds, it sort of pans upward.
You know, it's very cinematic and then boom, there's the one on the throne.
And notice gleaming metal and closing fire.
Yeah, right.
The same kind of layman as the mandanil saw, as St. John saw.
And there's this brightness of glory around him.
Sapphire throne is pretty awesome.
Sapphire throne, everybody.
And then finally there is that rainbow.
And that rainbow takes us back.
forward back to the future to revelation this time chapter four. Yeah yeah so in
Revelation four verses two and three this is now St. John of course speaking at
once I was in the spirit and behold a throne stood in heaven with one seated on
the throne and he who sat there had the appearance of Jasper and Carnelian and
and around the throne was a rainbow that had the appearance
of an emerald. So more gemstones and there's an emerald rainbow, you know, whether that means it's
all green or not, I don't know, but because I mean, that's what we think of when we think of
as emeralds, but yeah, gems. There's gems in the Bible are a whole thing. They're a whole thing.
It's not clear. Right. Yeah. They line up with with our gems. Well, and even I don't think I don't
remember if I've mentioned this on this show before but even even color
and ancient cultures don't necessarily line up with not just the way which colors were thinking of,
but the way colors are understood. Like, oh, we talked about they're not being blue, remember?
Yeah, right. You know, they can't see blue. And then, but then, or like, in, forgive me,
everybody, if I've said this before, I do not remember. But like, yellow in Beowulf is not the color
yellow, like we think of it, it's, it's really about the way that light plays on things. So,
So that's why water is often described as being yellow.
in Beowulf. It's not because they had super polluted water. It's because sunlight is playing
off of the top of it. So, yeah, anyway, yeah, colors and gems and stuff. Very interesting
rabbit hole. But so, once again, though, St. John is seeing the same things that the prophets
this includes the heavenly man. So then
This brings us to our next passage.
And to pull back the curtain for our listeners,
a great moment in our discussion,
our pre-show discussion was when you read,
I told you what we were gonna talk about
in terms of this passage.
You read the entire passage and then said,
I don't see what that has to do with anything.
All right.
I mean, it's, it's, it's, it's clearly like,
there's connections but I did not make,
Yeah, I did not
read this for the reason that we're one of the reasons that we're using this. But anyway,
so, you know, journey with me into my confusion, everybody. So, okay, so this is Exodus 24.
Yeah. Then, and I guess this is God speaking, right? Then he said to Moses, come up to the
Lord, you and Aaron, Nahab, Nadab and Abihu, and 70 of the elders of Israel and
worship from afar. Moses alone shall come near to the Lord, but the others shall not come near,
and the people shall not come up with him. Moses came and told the people all the words of the
Lord and all the rules, and all the people answered with one voice and said, all the words that the
Lord has spoken we will do. And Moses wrote down all the words of the Lord. He rose early in the
morning and built an altar at the foot of the mountain, and twelve pillars according to the
12 tribes of Israel, and he sent young men of the people
of Israel who offered burnt offerings and sacrificed peace offerings of oxen to the Lord.
And Moses took half of the blood and put it in basins, and half of the blood he threw
against the altar.
Then he took the book of the covenant and read it in the hearing of the people, and they
said, all that the Lord has spoken we will do and we will be obedient.
And Moses took the blood and threw it on the people and said, behold the blood of the covenant
that the Lord has made with you in accordance with all these words.
Then Moses and Aaron, Nadab and Abihu, and seventy of the elders of Israel went up, and
they saw the God of Israel.
There was under his feet as it were a pavement of sapphire stone, like the very heaven for
clearness, and he did not lay his hand on the chief men of the people of Israel.
They beheld God and ate and drank.
The Lord said to Moses, come up to me on the mountain and wait there, that I may give you
the tablets of stone with the law and the command.
which I have written for their instruction. So Moses rose with his assistant Joshua,
and Moses went up into the mountain of God, and he said to the elders,
wait here for us until we return to you, and behold, Aaron and Huir are with you,
whoever has a dispute, let him go to them. Then Moses went up on the mountain,
and the cloud covered the mountain. The glory of the Lord dwelt on Mount Sinai, and the cloud
covered it six days, and on the seventh day he called to Moses out
of the midst of the cloud. Now the appearance of the glory of the Lord was like a devouring fire
on the top of the mountain in the sight of the people of Israel. Moses entered the cloud and went
up on the mountain and Moses was on the mountain 40 days and 49. And just so you can again journey
with me into my confusion and reenact it, you can now richly participate in my confusion by listening
this. Father Stephen said so yeah so this has a lot about the Eucharist and everyone really need
understand this is being foundational for our understanding of the Eucharist. I was like,
okay, well I see blood. There's an altar, but I'm not really sure what else is going on here
with that. And it's a very Christmassy passage. Isn't it? The blood flying around and everything.
Yeah, um, right. So what this chapter is describing is the Covenant ratification.
ceremony of the old covenant, the first covenant, the covenant of Sinai.
So this is effectively the first Pentecost.
Yeah.
We tend to think of Pentecost as a New Testament as the first Pentecost, but the day of
Pentecost was already a feast.
Yeah, yeah, it was right.
The thing that happens in Acts is happening on an existing feast day, the Pentecost.
This is the fifth-yth day from the Passover.
Right.
that they've been brought out of Egypt,
they've been brought to Mount Sinai.
and now God is giving them the covenant.
And this ritual that we see play out here
that has two main parts is the ritual and actiment
of that covenant that represents the first Pentecost.
And the coming of the Holy Spirit is the second Pentecost.
And I definitely am not gonna go down this trail now,
but if we better understood
the relationship between first Panicost and second Panicost,
ritually, and what's going on in Acts.
We would better understand what St. Paul is talking about when he talks about the Torah or the law and the spirit.
But anyway,
we'll have to save that for a few days.
But so the first part, I said there's sort of these two parts, right, to this,
this covenant ratification ceremony.
The first one involves the blood of the covenant, right?
This is this is
where the Old Testament that phrase, the blood of the covenant occurs is in this chapter.
And so what we have here with the blood where half of it is taken and splattered on the
altar and then the other half gets sprinkled over the people, right?
That would be a very different theophany if we still did it that way.
Right.
Which I mean, dry cleaning bills.
Yeah.
It's just not going to come out.
Yeah, I think about how often you have to change your vestments.
But, but, I mean, you know, so some of this should be familiar to listeners,
you know, blood sprinkling.
It's about purification.
It's, you know, yeah, this is a normal part,
this is a normal part of sacrifice in the ancient world.
Right.
But this is a rare case where it's sprinkled on people.
On people and not just on altars and stuff and places,
but usually it's used to clean.
objects. Right? So there's this case where it's put on people. There's the
ordination of a priest that will probably talk about at some later point where
it's rubbed on the earlobe and the thumb and the toe. But there's a tease.
Yeah right there. But so yeah that's relatively rare. So what's going on with
this? This is an exercise in oath-taking. Right? And so to help understand what's
on here, we have to go back even a little further back into the book of Genesis.
Yes, and this looks at one of the weirdest passages in the Bible that I've had people
ask me about for years, you know, because people tend to ask priest questions.
And I was like, I don't know what this is about.
I mean, so this is the bit from, I mean, I do know.
But this is the bit from Genesis 15, right, where God makes this covenant with Abraham.
And pe-
P-
part of what goes on in this is various animals are cut into two pieces and they're laid out.
And then you see this torch pass between them, kind of go down the passage that's created
by these animal halves being laid out on the ground.
And that is just, I mean, from a modern point of view, like what is going on?
Yeah.
Well, yeah, and, and they're sort of when they're cutting half their butterfly, right?
Like it's bisected.
Like a spatch cocking.
And then you had it.
Yeah, yeah.
And laid on either side, right opposite each other.
And then after that's done, Abraham actually has to wait until nightfall for the torch to show
him and pass between them.
So it describes him in Genesis 15, having to like chase off the vultures and the buzzards.
Yeah.
don't eat this getting old.
stuff, getting at the bisected animals, right? So, yeah. So, what's going on here? Well,
the verb that's used for the issuing of a covenant, right? In Hebrew, we've talked about
covenants at least a little before on the show. I'm sure. I won't guess what episode again,
because I'm always wrong. But covenants are issued by like a hiking, by a suzerain to a
a vessel to a lesser-
right? They're given that. But the verb is an issued or signed or enacted or
inaugurated, but covenants are cut in Hebrew. Ha, you cut a covenant with
someone. Yeah. And this is what Abraham is doing is in the ancient Near East a
relatively common oath-taking ritual involved in these kind of
COVENANCE NORMALLY
it would be the vassal, it would be the weaker party who would walk through the split animals.
And what they're saying when they do that is as a form of oath-taking, they're saying
if I violate the terms of this covenant, right? Because covenants came with blessings and curses
attached, like you see at the end of the book of Deuteronomy, at the end of the Torah.
And so symbolic of those curses was the split animals.
Right. So it's sort of may I end up like these animals?
Right. Yeah. And then by walking through it, then the
vessel is identifying himself with the animals. But there's a sense of like, well,
the that's only going to happen to you if you break this covenant.
Right. You're accepting the curses that will come to you if you violate it.
Right. Yeah. You're excited to the curse of the covenant.
Now, what's interesting here, and this isn't the last time we're going to see this tonight,
But when this ritual
an act of ingeniousness, 15, God inverts it because it is the presence of God represented by
this torch that passes through the house. Right. It's not Abraham walking through or Abraham
at this point. Right. Abraham at this point. So effectively, God is saying that if this covenant
with Him is broken, He will receive the curses. Right. And for Abraham that or Abraham, he probably
would have thought, well God can't die.
So that just needs to be broken.
But what St. Paul will see in this, as he's going to talk about in several of his
epistles, is Christ becoming a curse for us.
Right?
Yeah.
That it is in fact Christ who accepts the curse of the covenant.
Right.
That results from our disobedience.
Right?
but so that this in going back to
Exodus, this blood that's thrown on the people, right, are taking, they're taking a similar
oath, right?
Yeah.
And you see that in the text, right?
Because after he does that, right, he puts it on them.
Well, actually, first in verse three, they say, all the words Lord is spoken, we will do.
He sprinkles it with the blood.
He reads it to them again.
And they say, all that the Lord is spoken, we will do.
We will be obedient.
Liars.
But anyway.
Right.
Yes.
A narrator, they were not obedient.
And when he's throwing, and then verse 8, when he's throwing the blood on the people, he
says, behold, the blood of the covenant that the Lord has made with you.
And it coordinates with all these words.
Yes.
Look at the blood.
So, the idea is basically we're accepting death if we break it.
You know?
Yeah.
Right.
So, uh...
This is sort of part one, as we said, there's two parts.
Yeah, yeah. Part two then comes in verse 9 through 11, where Moses, Aaron the
high priest, his sons, Nate Abbot Abahoo, who they don't know yet, but are not
long for this world, C. Leviticus, had the 70 elders of Israel, 70 or 72, elders
of Israel, go part way up the mountain.
Moses is going to go all the way to the top. Right.
Just speak to God face to face and receive the covenant.
But they go halfway up these seventy three to seventy five others.
And we're told very bluntly, they see the God of Israel.
Right. Yeah.
That's what it says.
They saw the God of Israel.
And then they see under his feet this pavement of sapphire stones.
Right.
And and notice under his feet.
So we don't have his body described the way we did.
in the other prophetic text we look at,
but he does have feet.
Yeah, and it's interesting to me
that in verse 11, it says,
he did not lay his hand on the chief men
of the people of Israel, which I assume that means
they didn't die when they saw God.
Right, they were not harmed.
Yeah.
Yeah, no death by holiness at this point.
Yes.
Again, see Leviticus.
Yeah.
And remember, this is a mountain where,
if an animal touched it,
had to kill it from a distance.
Yeah, they couldn't even go so that they wouldn't touch the mountain themselves try to get the animal and kill it for touching the mountain
Yeah, I mean if I recall correctly
There's all kinds of purification stuff that they have to do before this happen. Yes, right? Yes
Yes, yes, but so the second piece of this covenant
ratification or this covenant cutting
Samoy is the eating of this meal
right
God is there in
human form in their midst
Right.
And they are...
this sacrificial meal with him and establishing this fellowship between them as
the leadership of Israel and God himself. Right? So these are these two pieces and the
point I made that at first confused you but hopefully now you think makes sense.
It does indeed make sense. That you see these two elements that this is this is the
moment.
at the mystical supper, the last supper, as Christ is instituting the Eucharist, this
is the moment that he takes us back to when he says, this is my blood of the new covenant.
This is referring us back to this. This is my blood of the new covenant. And there is this
element of oath taking here. So I'm about to hold
under your hats people. I'm about to say something kind of positive about Ulrich's wingly.
Right. So a lot of folks who have heard of Ulrich's wingly may think that his view of the
Eucharist in particular and the sacraments in general was that they were in scare quotes
Just symbolic right right and I did this scare quotes don't at me Jonathan Pigeaux
So, right.
But that's not actually...
Call it a mouth like that, man.
That's not actually what Zwingli...
What Zwingli taught about it.
Zwingli himself, right.
Zwingli himself took up an older meaning of the Latin word sacramentum.
Yes, right.
Which means, which is a means taking an oath.
and oath and cuz
like Roman soldiers would have to do a sacramentum to join the army.
Right.
The sacred oath.
Yeah.
And so, right, Zwingli was not wrong that there is an element of oath-taking in baptism
in the Eucharist.
Right.
He was wrong that they're just an act of oath-taking.
Yeah.
Right.
He was wrong that that was all he thought they were, but they are that.
He was, he was.
right about that piece, right? So there you go. That's the one positive thing that
we're likely to ever say about Hold Runs Bingley. Oh, Lord of Spirits. Yes. Yes. There was
a piece of content edited for time in which I said something positive about Michelle
Foucault sitting wonder what that could have been. But yes. So, but so there is this and
there is this oath-taking element in the Eucharist.
And we see this play out.
in the institution, right, in the mystical supper,
in the last supper, with Judas and the dipping of the bread,
right?
And Christ saying that someone would betray him,
this idea of faithfulness and loyalty and betrayal,
break it.
And that is incorporated right into the institution
at the beginning of the Eucharist.
And we still, in our Orthodox practice, right?
In the pre-communian prayers, we talk about,
neither will I give the echises to Judas,
like the
I confess thee, right? There is this idea of faithfulness. I will not speak of thy mystery,
so thine enemies. There is contained within those prayers, it brings out this element of oath and
of sort of a re-ratification of the covenant that each of us has broken. It continues to break,
but we are reconfirming it as we're being purified by the blood of Christ in the Eucharist.
right and so
both the blood and the meal are within this sacrificial context.
So this is not, we've talked about how the Eucharist is sacrificial,
but this is a very particular referent
that in terms of the blood of the new covenant and what is going on here,
this connection to the original Pentecost and Exodus,
and just as an aside, because I feel that need to do this.
Some folks, now I have to say some folks are all.
older man, I'm an old man. Some of you who are old enough to remember when the movie
Passion of the Christ came out, which is not all of you. Right. I feel like it wasn't that long ago.
But it was. But, man, it's because I mean, you're only a few months older than I am. There was
there was one, there was one line that was edited out of the subtitles.
Okay.
From the air mag.
And it was aligned from St. Matthew's gospel, where the crowd that is
for by the way, 2004.
Yeah.
So about to be 18 years ago, man.
Get off my lawn anyway.
And that was a line for St. Matthew's gospel, where the crowd is crying out for
Christ to be crucified.
And they say his blood be upon us and upon our children, right?
Right.
Yeah.
And there's this whole history in medieval Western Europe,
a blood libel and all of this nonsense
that is a complete misinterpretation.
Right.
It's the least anti-Semitic thing.
Yes, sir.
Yeah, because I mean, it's, you know,
when blood is put upon you,
richually within Israel, that's good.
Right.
That's restoring the covenant.
It could broke it.
Right.
there is clueless
in, say Matthew is referencing this in Exodus, right, and the blood of the covenant that
was placed on the Israelites and their children, right, to re-ratify the covenant and the new
covenant, right? So, this is, say Matthew is using it as this ironic thing. This is something
we see a lot in the gospels where some people who aren't believers per se will sort of say
something that turns out to be true anyway, right? Yeah.
Yeah.
It happens to Gamelio already.
Yes.
They don't necessarily mean it the way it comes.
And this is the same kind of thing.
This is a crowd being for blood, right?
But they end up saying something that means something far more profound than they realize.
And that's what there's a certain irony there that St. Matthew is trying to bring out.
But anyway, that's kind of a decided it's related to that text that we were talking about.
But so the reason I said that so.
foundational to the Eucharist is that I mean this is why we are coming together to to eat a meal to
receive the blood of the new covenant with Christ in our midst in the same way that he stood halfway
up Mount Sinai with the elders of Israel and Aaron and Moses and they dab and have a who as they ate
before him. And so now for the rest of the second half we have
Yeah, Pope Prairie!
Yeah, this is just...
versus versus. Yeah, yeah, where we are about to take a series of verses out of context.
Yes, but we're not we're not doing it in a irresponsible way. Okay.
We just don't want to.
It's a belabor the point in some circuitous, wondering journey.
Get to our top.
Yes. Okay. So all right. Well, just this we sort of, you know,
lightning round. So okay so Genesis 26
26, 24, you know, this is God appearing to Isaac.
And the Lord appeared to him the same night and said,
I am the God of Abraham, your father, fear not,
for I am with you and will bless you and multiply your offspring
for my servant, Abraham's sake.
So it's very explicit there, it says the Lord appeared to him.
He sees him.
Yes.
You know, right, right.
Anything else we want to say about that?
No, this is lightning around man.
All right, lightning around.
Okay.
Just this is, just this is 2813.
And this is, this is Jacob's ladder, right?
Is it a girl?
Yeah.
Yeah, as Jacob's Ziggurat, excuse me.
And behold, the Lord stood above it.
I see I needed an antecedent for that it.
And behold, the Lord stood above it and said,
I am the Lord, the God of Abraham, your father and the God of Isaac,
the land on which you lie, I will give to you and to your offspring.
So you get God.
standing above it. He's not only
seasoned, but he sees him standing, which means it wasn't like some ball of light.
Or whatever. It's somebody voice. Yeah. Yeah. It's got. He's got legs and feet at least, you know,
just standing going on. Okay.
Genesis 32. I could read all the way 22 through 32. I'm not going to read all of it. I'm just going to read verse 30.
That's all the rassling.
This is the rassling scene.
Jacob rastling the angels.
So Jacob called the name of the place,
Peniel, I've heard it pronounce Peniel,
saying, for I have seen God face to face,
and yet my life has been delivered.
What does that word mean, Father Stephen?
It means the face of God.
Yeah, right.
God's face.
Yeah, usually in the Bible when you see,
and so so and so called the place this,
for he said.
Then usually there's just the explanation of what the word the name means. You know, like,
you know, Bethel, for this is the house of God, you know, whatever. That's what's going on here.
Yeah. And let's be here. Jacob doesn't say he wrestled with an angel. He says he wrestled with God.
With God, Jacob, which is what Israel means, by the way, also, but wrestles with God.
Yeah. Yeah. Okay. Exist 33 11. Very famous. Thus the Lord used to speak to Moses,
face.
to face as a man speaks to his friend. When Moses turned again into the camp his assistant
Joshua the son of none a young man would not depart from the tent.
So yeah, Joshua is seeing him too. Right, right. And yeah, face to face. Yeah, Joshua is
not. Yeah, it's interesting. You know, think about Josh. I mean, we think about the book
of Joshua and him leading all those battles and stuff. But Joshua is having these, these
visionary experiences of the Lord alongside Moses.
at least this occasion. Are there other places too where Joshua sees Moses?
Yes, of course he's got the commander of the Lord's Army.
Right? Right?
Yes, he's not just sort of this...
And oh by the way this is Moses' assistant.
This is some beacon.
Yes, no, there's something much bigger happening here.
that was kind of the lightning round of various other places that you can see where
where people see God and clearly see a physical form and in some cases clearly with human
characteristics, right? Standing a face, a couple of times of a face. Yeah.
And you know, when in all of these particular examples, when people see God, they're seeing
Christ, right? Right. Like when you when you have a vision of God in the Bible, if you kind of default
to this is Christ, that's pretty much accurate 99% of the time.
99.999, yeah.
Yeah, right.
Yes, at least,
couple other hands and other things.
But yeah.
That's what St. Justin Margers said at least.
So I'll go with St. Justin.
Yes, yeah.
So our first two halves to do the teas now,
our first two halves we've talked about the heavenly man.
Yes.
Right.
third half.
Now, we're going to talk about the man from heaven.
All right, well, we're going to take a short break
and we will be right back.
Father Andrew Stephen Daymak and Father Stephen DeYoung
will be back in a moment to take your calls on the next part
of the Lord of Spirits. Give them a call at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF Radio.
I
Hey, this is John Maddox.
You know when you support Ancient Faith Radio,
you're not only helping to make this ministry possible
for you, but also for people like Bryce in Australia.
I'd firstly just like to say that I love your show
and what you do.
It means a lot to all of us listening.
I'm down in Australia and over here,
orthodoxy is basically unheard of.
I'm not orthodox.
I was raised into an evangelical Protestant family.
However, from a gradual exposure and desire to live
more about orthodoxy. I've come to agree and see truth in pretty much everything that
church teaches. The nearest English-speaking orthodox church is several hours away and I
feel all alone in my pursuit of the faith. Currently my only exposure to orthodoxy is
through ancient faith radio and my friend. How should I introduce the idea that I may
be inquiring into orthodoxy to my parents? Thanks again, Bruce.
Would you consider a donation to AFR right now? You can do so on our app or go to our website
AncientFaith.com-slaSH-Support.
Ancient Faith Radio.
Here for you and for people all over the world.
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits, the Father-Andre-Styven Day.
and Father Stephen DeYoung.
If you have a question, call now at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF radio.
Welcome back. It's the third half of the show.
And this will be the final segment in our series
that we've been doing on the Christology of the Old Testament.
I really like this series.
this series, I think it's been really valuable for me.
and a lot of the feedback we've gotten has been very, very good.
So, you know, thanks for sticking with us, everybody.
I know that this stuff has not been quite as, I don't know,
whiz-bang spectacular as, you know, monsters and giants and stuff.
But, but no, I had to say.
It's a bit of an sodium act.
Yeah. Okay. Right.
We did, there is a good payoff here in this episode.
You have to come on.
I think that should be a t-shirt.
I don't know how it would work, but yeah,
some kind of Babylonian something.
You
night only, Jerubin Zodiac, you know, you have tour dates on the back with like Sumerian
and Acadian cities. Make it happen, t-shirt maker, you know who you are. We're counting on you
down there in Florida. So okay, but before we get into the third half, I just want to give everybody
heads up. So, you know, we do our shows in the second and fourth Thursdays of the
month this month, this December, there's five Thursdays and whenever there's a month
with five Thursdays, that always means it's going to be three weeks between episodes at
some point.
So our next episode is going to be three weeks from tonight on the 13th, I think, of January.
And we're going to be doing another all Q and A episode.
So sometimes when people call in and they have a question that's not really about what
we're talking about in this particular episode.
ask him to hold it for later or send us an email or something like that. But in the next
episode, there will be none of that.
Call in with filter. No, call in with what?
Go screening. No, there will be screens. Tell us about how you're from another dimension.
Tell us you're a time traveler. That I want to hear talk about, you know, how your brothers
There's the Nephilim.
Anything goes, man.
Pretty much.
The gloves are coming off.
So yeah, maybe another pandemonium episode next time.
So yeah, so get ready.
You know, we've had to ask a number of people to hold it for a number of episodes here.
But the floodgates are coming open next time.
So yeah, yeah, that'll be at the turn of the year.
It'll be our first episode of the year.
Again, that'll be on the 13th of January.
So, all right, well.
Well now we're going to talk about, I mean this is one of my favorite passages in Scripture
actually.
So this is Genesis chapter 18 and this is the very famous oak of Mema scene.
And a lot happens here but I'm just going to read the very very beginning of this.
And the Lord appeared to him, that is to Abraham, by the oaks of Mema as he sat at the door
of his tent in the heat of the day.
He lifted up his eyes and looked.
and behold, three men were standing in front of him, when he saw them, he ran from the tent door
to meet them and bowed himself to the earth and said, O Lord, if I have found favor in your sight,
do not pass by your servant. Let a little water be brought, and wash your feet and rest yourselves
under the tree, while I bring a morsel of bread that you may refresh yourselves, and after that,
you may pass on since you have come to your servant. So they said, do as you have said.
Abraham went quickly into the tent to Sarah and said,
quick, three sails of fine flour needed and make cakes.
And Abraham ran to the herd and took a calf tender and good,
and gave it to a young man who prepared it quickly.
Then he took curds and milk and the calf that he had prepared
and set it before them.
And he stood by them under the tree while they ate.
So, you know, at the beginning,
We've got Abraham sitting in the door of his tent.
And when we were doing our pre-show prep, you commented that the injured world must have
had a much higher tolerance for boredom.
You'd be just sitting there in the door of his tent.
But here's the way I, this is my head cannon for Genesis 18, if I may, is that most Middle
Eastern men sitting there in the door, and of course Abraham is older at this point.
So, you know, most elderly Middle Eastern men sitting around.
what is he likely doing? He's probably playing backgammon because that is what what
Middle Eastern men of a certain age tend to do when they're just sort of sitting
around retired. And I said that and you you mentioned to me that there was
something called the Royal Game of Ur. You are. So what would tell us what that is?
Father Stephen. So this is the earliest known board game and we're actually the
The earliest...
known board game. We have complete game boards that date back to 2600 BC. Right. And so now when
is Abraham roughly about 2000. So this is 600 years pre Abraham. We have boards. Yes. Yes.
And good. Yeah. Well, we, the reason it's called the royal game of war is that these early
boards, the earliest boards we found were in the sort of royal burial grounds. I got you royal cemetery
at or.
So it's very clear that the wealthy folks were doing it already back in 2600.
Right. And I mean, the fun thing is is that there actually are clay,
Q&A-form tablets with the rules for this game.
Yes.
Which is crazy. And so here's the other thing.
It turns out that it's very likely that this is in fact a precursor to backgammon.
So...
Look it up. There is a whole Wikipedia article on the Royal Game of Orr and as soon as you see the game board
Which they have a picture of it one of the ones that's in the British Museum and
It will remind you of a backgammon board everybody
So when I made that joke about Abraham sitting around playing backgammon
It's possible it is indeed possible that he was playing something like this and here's the other fun thing everybody
you can go on Amazon and order yourself a
replica copy of this game. Now when I was telling my wife about this at lunch today, she's like,
oh yeah, the kids and I printed out a copy of that game board and we've played it.
So there it is everybody, my wife once again way ahead of me. It almost every respect.
I'm pretty sure any kind of trademark or copyright from 2600 BC has long lapsed.
So you probably just make your own. Yeah.
It's true, you don't have to buy the expensive one.
Amazon, but it does look just like the one in the British Museum. So that is cool. So yes, so
Abraham's out there playing back in the door of his tent. So hypothetically. Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah,
throwing that out there as well. Yeah. Yeah. And so but what he's doing, he sees we have this first
description of three men, right? Right. Three men are at that. Yeah, everybody does this in their
English Translate.
including the way you behold three men were standing in front of him. This is a little inside football for the language nerds
That behold there is translating a Hebrew
It's not really a particle. It's a Hebrew word Hane
and
Hane really should not be translated
The behold thing comes from that's how the
the
The King James said it to do it.
Be home, or low, or...
Low would be hold. Yeah, I'm a big fan of low.
Low.
Yeah. And really the idea is the word is just put there to lend a sense of sort of immediacy to the action.
Hmm. Right. So when I'm doing translations, I would put more like and suddenly three men were standing in front of it.
Oh, right. Or immediately or that kind of idea. Right.
Yeah. It almost it almost has a parallel with the old English quat,
which I do tend to translate it
low but it might mean listen up or you know although I did see one translation this one drove me crazy
it transited as well. So the first word in Beowulf is well. Well we have heard how in the days of
all I'm like oh please no please don't. So like three minutes. Yeah so like. Yeah. Yeah.
Yeah. Yeah. I think what actually would work here as an old English translation of this
this.
That's right.
know, but so he looks up and they're there, right? Yeah. And so he then offers this hospitality,
right? Where he invites them in, washes their feet, has Sarah prepare some food, right? She
starts making some cakes. He goes to the herd and gets a calf to cook it. And then he goes, he puts
it together and he feeds them.
right? And they eat. And we're going to discover very clearly you left off at the end of verse 8.
That verse, it verses that you're supposed to. It's fine. Okay.
No shame. Uh, it verses died through 15 when the central one of these figures speaks. It's just
identified as being Yahweh. Right. The God of Israel. And then two, two other figures who will be
identified a little later but we'll get to that.
Yeah, and verse.
And it says, the Lord said, and of course again is the all caps, Lord.
So Yahweh said, right.
And so one of these three is Yahweh the God of Israel, right?
And notice Yahweh the God of Israel has his feet washed and eats in front of Abraham.
Important details, right?
So this is a person, right?
Yeah, the sense of not in the theological sense of personhood.
but in the sense of, right, it's a man human, right?
Yeah, human body, right?
Yeah, and instead of appearance,
and tactile experience.
Yeah, and not only,
you know, are you getting the look of a man,
but he does things like, have his feet washed and eat.
So like, this works like a man.
It, you know, yeah, right?
Right?
Which should remind us of something.
Yes, yeah.
Right.
But so one of these things in particular so one of the things that I know we've been breaking people's brains with a little bit
Is the wibbly wobbly time you want me stuff right which is talking about whether
When Christ appears to the Old Testament in bodily form whether that is
Would look like or would whether that's his
resurrected human body from the incarnation
Right, right?
And we can...
because we have locked it right,
that well, this is pre-incarnation, right, quote unquote,
right, because for the humans involved, right,
this is an earlier point in time,
the incarnation, Christ's incarnation
had not entered into the realm of human conscious experience
yet, right, it was not a phenomenological reality yet.
But as we've also talked about, Christ is God,
Yeah, and so asking this is the problem of asking what time it is in heaven right now, right?
Right.
That that time and space don't apply.
So the same way that Christ's body, sorry, Calvinist and the extra Calvinist to come, is
not in some particular place and not others.
Right. After the resurrection of dissension, the same way, it's not at a particular point
in time. Right? God is not like on a parallel track of time with us, any more than he's occupying
physical space somewhere.
Yeah, and the reason why this makes sense is this person in front of Abraham who is having
his feet washed and his eating.
This isn't fake
Yeah, you know that you know
So this is a human body right and his eating here's where this becomes really pointed and that's the eating
right because in we we did I
Remember when this was
This was back at Posca time this year. Yeah, we talked about the resurrection appearances of Christ
Yeah, yeah, and one of the things that happens over and over again in the resurrection
the action appearances of...
Christ is that Christ eats in front of the disciples.
In front of them.
Yeah.
In order to show that he's risen from the dead,
that he's not a ghost or a spirit or a phantom
or whatever, but he's actually risen.
Who's that by eating?
Yeah.
So, this causes a kind of a problem
then with Exodus 18, if you read it in a certain way, right?
Because if we're gonna view this as the pre- and,
quote unquote pre-intrarn-
Christ. And we view the quote unquote pre incarnate Christ as bodyless. Then how is he eating?
And if the pre incarnate Christ, right, quote unquote, who has not yet taken upon himself
our human nature, not yet from our perspective, right, can eat. Then how did Christ after
the resurrection, eating, prove anything.
Right.
And.
You know, the only other, like there's another bad way to solve this problem, which is to say
that he was incarnate more than once.
Right.
A very bad.
Yes.
Yeah, like this is a human body that he's got for this moment, and then oh, by the way,
he takes one later from the Virgin.
Right.
So nobody's wants to go there.
Yeah.
Right.
Or there's a very simple way through this.
That just as Christ is the Lamb's Lane from before the foundation of the world.
Right.
Part of the reason we could say Christ was incarnate, Christ took upon himself, our shared human nature without change.
Right. Is that there's not for Christ as God before and after.
Yeah. Right. Which a place, there's a place where these eternal realities enter into our human conscious experience, our phenomenological experience.
Right. The realm of time and space that we live in.
But that doesn't mean that they were not true for God at some point in the past and are true now.
And some change has taken place.
Yeah, and it's also why one of the reasons we can say that he is the first born overall creation.
You know, not just in the sense that he is the first born in terms of his position where he gives the inheritance,
which is probably the most important thing to say about that.
but also there is even a more literal way that he is the first
over all creation in the sense that he is man even at this point, you know, that it's
in fact he is the man. I mean when you see icons of Christ creating Adam and Christ as a
man, I mean what do you do with that if you can't read it in an essentially a sort of
trans temporal way. Right. Right. And we have to do that we
We have to and do do this elsewhere in archaeology.
So if you are an orthodox Christian, then you believe that God the Son is eternally
generated from God the Father without time.
Right?
That Christ is begotten of the Father, not in time.
Yeah, there's so many theological problems that come by sort of assuming that God is
bound by linear time.
I mean, just, you know, we could, yeah, we could just list them off by the hundreds.
Uh, it's really true.
You know, this is where I get to say, sorry, not sorry, Calvinists.
Uh, but, but it's, but I mean, it really is true.
Like, and we have to take it really seriously and not just say, well, you know,
because the way that, the way that most Christians, I think, take that seriously on
some level is by talking about, you know, God knowing the future.
right, they'll say, well, it's sort of present for him all.
the same time, which absolutely, right? But they don't always follow that out or they
couldn't be. Yes, but right. Right. Right. Like, let's follow out what that really means.
And the fact that here you have, let's just say it, Jesus Christ's eating with Abraham,
I mean, there's no other way to kind of work that out. He's actually eating. You know,
Angel's Doni, right?
Although it says, I don't know, this is a question that I have.
because it says at least in the translation that I read he stood by them under the tree while they
ate. Yeah it's ambiguous. It's ambiguous. Okay in the Hebrew. Yeah. Okay. Um while the eating happened. Yeah.
And so just to further our case a little bit. Right. Okay. Before someone comes along and says why are
you're bringing all this play-doh eternity stuff into my Bible right so
If you know who says what we were just saying,
that would be Christ himself in John 8 verse 56.
Right. Right. Which, you know, he says,
your father Abraham rejoiced that he would see my day.
He saw it and was glad.
Like if you stopped at just the first sentence,
you might think, oh, Abraham's rejoicing
that someday in the future when he's in heaven,
heaven. He's gonna see this happening.
But then Jesus puts it immediately in the past tense. He saw it and was glad.
Right. And remember my day, we talked about day, like the day of the Lord, right?
This is the day, right? This is not a way of referring to a 24-hour calendar period, right?
This is a way of referring to a happening, right?
Something coming into the the the real for dollars. So yes, Abraham
sat and ate with Christ and washed his feet. Yeah, Ed was glad when he saw the Lord. So yes, and notice also it's also in St. John's Gospel
by the way where Christ washes the disciples feet, where this pattern, and again, this is not the last time we're going to see this tonight, this pattern is inverted.
Right?
Christ washes the disc-
Cyples feet. It says he did not come to be served but to serve. Yeah, he flips it. Right.
Right. And comes to serve. And more on that in just a minute.
So yeah, as we mentioned in verses 9 through 15, there's the whole exchange with
about Sarah having a son where she's back in the tent and she laughs because she's like 90 and
Abraham's 100 and she's like, yeah, sure, I'm going to have a kid.
and that makes...
clear that this is Yahweh who's speaking. And then there's this really interesting thing that
happens in verses 17 through 20 where Abraham kind of shuffles out and Yahweh has a conversation
with Yahweh. Right, yeah. In verse 16 it says that Abraham leaves. Right, the men went
said out from there and they looked down towards Sodom and Abraham went with them to set them on
on their way. So Abraham is seeing them to...
Well, not the door because it's just a series of tents, but he's taking them presumably to the edge of the camp and then you see this conversation happening between
Yahweh and Yahweh. Yeah. Yeah, where the first thing is says is
The Lord said, you know, shall I hide from Abraham what I'm what I'm about to do
Seeing that Abraham so surely become a great and mighty nation and all the nations of the earth should be blessed in him
and he goes on but the point is he's saying,
you know, shall I hide what I'm about to do?
do to Sodom and Gomorrah, right, from Abraham. And then there's this response. In verse 20,
then the Lord said again, then Yahweh said, because the outcry against Sodom and Gomorrah is great,
and their sin is very grave, I will go down to see whether they have done altogether,
according to the outcry that has come to me. And if not, I will know. So there's this question that's
ask and then there's a response given. So it's clear that the Lord is talking to the Lord.
And then the Lord responds to the Lord.
Right?
Yeah.
So, I mean, who's, is this the father and the son?
Is that what we're seeing here?
Yes.
Yeah.
Right.
And so, note also that language, restoring one of, of, I will go down to see.
Right?
Yeah.
Which doesn't make any sense if you take that purely in human terms.
Oh God isn't sure what's happening down there.
He's got a lot of people who are inside him and
so he's going to go have a look.
He's heard bad things, but he needs to go see for himself.
Right? No. Right?
God knows what's going on.
But that I will go down to see is echoing this language.
We're only in Genesis 18.
Right? So really seven chapters out from the tower of Babel in Genesis 11.
Right? And remember, with building the tower,
there was the lettuce go down and see.
They were trying to draw God down and God says,
well, we'll go down.
And then that's when the judgment happens.
This is when he comes to visit, right?
And God visits his people.
It's not like grandpa coming over and having, you know,
scones and coffee, right?
It's this visit is more like wait till your father gets home,
right?
This is.
That's some stuff's going to get settled.
Right.
And don't make me come down there.
Yeah.
Um, yes.
So that's I will pull this car over.
That's it.
Where so this is this is judgment stuff.
This is judgment stuff, right?
Yeah.
And so we're going to go again to the gospel of John.
Right. Okay. Yeah. Yeah. And then I mean, so everybody knows John 316 for God so
of the world that he gave his only son that whoever believes in him should not perish
forever lasting life. John 317 verse after four. In other words, because four God did not
send his son into the world to condemn the world, but in order that the world might be saved
through him. So it's, it's, uh,
yeah.
again in the inversion. In this case, God does come down, but it's not this time to
condemn. It's to save. Right. And as St. Paul says, you know, do not say who will go up to
heaven that is to draw God down. Right. Right. For no one will ascend, but he who descended
that he might fill all things. Right. This is this is the same Bible language that St.
Paul plays with but why does St. John have to say this right because
The coming of the Lord, the day of the Lord, is darkness where all things are tried by fire.
But when Christ comes, this is how He inverts that pattern. It's not just that rather than having
His feet washed, He washes the disciples feet. It's not just that rather than enacting the
curses of the covenant upon those who have broken it, He becomes a curse for us.
right, so that we can receive the blessings, right, and receive the new
covenant, but it's that his entire visit is not for condemnation and judgment in that
sense, but for salvation.
Yeah.
Right.
Cool.
So when when the heavenly man becomes the man from heaven, right?
He comes to bring salvation, not judgment in his incarnation.
The second coming then, right?
Christ glorious appearing is a different story.
Yeah, and back to the pattern.
Right, right. And so then as as the chapter sort of concludes, right, the the the other two men, right?
So you always say it talks to Abraham and Abraham, of course, kind of does his intercessory haggling, right?
If we could find 50 people, right, will you spare the cities? If we want if we can find 25, what do we
maybe 5, 10, right?
Yeah.
Meanwhile, meanwhile, the other, the two,
and it says this in 191, next chapter.
that the two angels then arrive in Sodom.
Right, so that identifies the other two figures.
So this is Yahweh the God of Israel and two angels.
Right, it's not Father, Son, and Holy Spirit.
The three. And the sort of culmination of this judgment is in chapter 19 verse 24,
in which Yahweh the God of Israel sends down fire from Yahweh the God of Israel.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
And that's the end.
No, this actually is the last detail we're going to talk about.
But the interesting thing here is not the spectacular destruction of these cities.
It says, then the Lord reigned on Sodom and Gomorrah, sulfur and fire from the Lord out of heaven.
Again, Lord, there is Yahweh. Yahweh reigned on Sodom and Gomorrah, sulfur and fire from Yahweh out of heaven.
So you've got Yahweh sending down fire from Yahweh in heaven.
So there's this...
location identification for the one sending down the fire. So again it's Yahweh here
and Yahweh there simultaneously, who are interacting and in two places. Yes. Right. Yes.
Yeah. Well, this is the end of our series on Old Testament Christology.
I think there's so many possible takeaways from all of these, but I think that the one,
for me, not just this particular episode, but from all four of them, really.
We've mentioned a number of times there's this phrase in the scripture, no one can see God.
Whether it's no one can see, no one has seen God at any time, or no one can see God and live.
This idea that God is invisible is certainly there in the Scriptures and yet there are all these places
where he does appear even before the events of the Gospels, right? Even before that. And, and, and if you've listened to these episodes, now you have no excuse for ever saying again, well, God was totally invisible in the Old Testament,
and then he suddenly appeared on the scene in the New Testament. That's just not a thing. I'm sorry, which sometimes people say that as, as our explanation for why we have iconography.
There's something true about that.
We do have iconography because the Lord appeared, because he became man. That is true. But if you go
on to say that he had never appeared before the events in the Gospels, well, that's not true.
It's very clearly, very clearly not true. So, you know, what are we to do with that, right? You
know, these statements in scripture that no one has seen God? Well, the easy answer to that is no
I want to see God.
unless they're looking at Christ and then they're seeing God.
Right?
The point of the scripture saying, you know, no one has seen God,
is not to like lay down a rule about the nature of God.
Right? You know, as people who live in the 21st century west,
we're very influenced by a lot of philosophical movements
that we liked
lay things out in big taxonomies, and we want to understand systems of knowledge. And so,
you know, the underlying question in a lot of our thought is the question, what is this?
Right? So we want to define it. We want to describe it. We want to give it a Latin name.
You know, all of these things, which I mean, there's something good about a lot of that kind of work,
for sure. And yet, the main question to ask when encountering...
the God of Abraham Isaac and Jacob is not what is God, which is what's underlying when we try to
work out the apparent contradiction between you can't see God and wait here he is,
right? Because we're trying to figure out what's the nature of God that sometimes he is a parent and
sometimes he's not. You know, not that questions about the nature of God are not important,
But the most important question is who is this?
And you notice that Jesus asks us to disciples that question, who do you say to that I am?
Who do men say that I am? He doesn't ever ask them the question, what am I?
Right? And occasionally when they tend in that direction, they say things like it's a, you know,
especially after his resurrection, it's a ghost. You know,
they obviously get that very, very wrong. It's who am I? Right? And
And the answer to that question is, well, everything we've...
just been discussing these last four episodes. Right? And the point is that God reveals Himself
to us. And the point of that is, as we've just been hearing, so that we may be saved. Right? God
That is not a natural phenomenon.
He very deliberately shows himself to us...
So that we can be saved.
It's not just a display as power.
It's not, it doesn't just sort of happen.
It's specifically so that we can be saved,
so that we can be rescued from these fallen gods
that we've heard about so many times,
so that we can be rescued from our own rebellion
and joining in that demonic evil, right?
So that we can be rescued from corruption and death.
that we can be rescued from our sins, which drag us into all of those things, all of that kind of slavery.
Right? Everything that God does in relation to man is for the purpose of saving him. The
technical theological term for this is what's called the so-terriological motive.
And God has a so-terriological motive, or if we can speak of him, you know, about his motives.
It does say in Scripture.
that God is not willing that any should perish,
but that all men should be saved
and come to the knowledge of the truth.
That is his desire.
We know it's his desire because he said it is.
He wants to save us.
And so when he appears to us, it's for that purpose.
It's not about creating systems or taxonomies of knowledge.
Whenever we see an appearance of God in Scripture,
whenever we see the appearance of God
in the divine services, whenever we see the appearance
of God in iconography, when we see the appearance of God
in the writings of the f***.
fathers, or wherever, however we encounter them, when we see the appearance of God in the
love and the kindness shown to us by another person, it is always for our salvation.
So we should ask the question, how is this for my salvation?
How can I receive this so that I can be saved?
How can I receive this so that I can participate in his work in the world so that all can be
saved?
Right?
We have to work for the salvation of all.
We're not told that all will be saved.
is a heresy to insist that all will be saved. I'm sorry, it just is. Sorry, not sorry,
universalists. It is a heresy, but we are to work for the salvation of all because God
is working for the salvation of all, right? And so when we see these appearances of the
Lord, whether we're talking about him as the angel of the Lord, the word of the Lord,
son of man and then these amazing expressions
from this episode, the heavenly man, the man from heaven. Right? When we see him, it is always,
you can see it's always in relation to what he's doing for mankind. Every time it's all about that,
this is the divine mission. This is the gospel, right? His victory over demons and in death.
So, and notice all of this is done in the revelation.
of Christ in the revelation of Christ. Sometimes you know some of the church fathers will say things like
what are we trying to attain to a trying to attain to the vision of Christ and someone might say well
uh you know that's what salvation is it's like seeing him like how does what does that do but if you
understand what seeing him does to you and what it does for you and why he's doing it because you
You don't see him without him willing it to happen.
Then you understand.
that the vision of Christ in glory
transforms the human person to become like him.
That's what it does.
You're not just sort of viewing him, right?
It's not just a sight or a spectacle.
It is a vision in which you participate.
We read from some of these prophets about how,
when they saw God, it just sort of knocked them off their socks.
Uh...
you know, it's because they were participating in his holiness.
There was a transformative effect.
And of course, in multiple cases, we see it calling a prophet, giving him what he needs
in order to be a prophet in order to bring the word of the Lord to the people.
Right?
So the question always is, how is this for my salvation?
Whatever we receive from the Lord is for our salvation.
all of it. There's there's not a thing
that we receive in this life that is not for our salvation.
It's that pervasive, that overwhelming, that beautiful.
And so I just thank God for the things that I've learned.
And I hope that you've learned some things
during this series.
And it's been a great 2021 for the podcast.
And we have a lot more coming in the next year.
So
So, but my prayer is always is that you would attain to seeing our Lord God and Savior Jesus Christ as He is.
Father Stephen?
So, I'm going to actually hear my final thoughts.
Answer a speak pipe that we didn't play.
That's cool.
It's live radio and I'm going rogue.
We got to speak pipe from a certain, I don't know if she
identifies as a batwoman or a batgirl.
And there's batgirl within without the hyphen.
So whichever female,
character and humanoid she identifies as,
said as a speakpipe that we didn't play.
It would be good if I thought of this
and told you beforehand, wouldn't it?
It's okay with it.
But anyway, to summarize it,
Talk about a certain difficulty that I think is not just hers, but maybe some other listeners
in that sort of a lot of the stuff we talk about in this series and in general on this
show could be very heady and very nerdy, right?
And appeal intellectually especially to a certain type of person and get them excited and
interested, but sometimes there is a
disconnect between that and sort of everyday life, even life in the church, even like going
to liturgy, right?
The actual practical thing of getting in the car on a Sunday morning without coffee and
driving to liturgy, right?
It can seem at a distance from sort of these heavy, fascinating sort of intellectual
type discussions.
And the question was sort of about how to
how to connect those dots or how to bridge that gap.
And I don't think this is just like a problem with our show,
right? Like we need to fix the show and make it more practical.
I think this is a problem that more and more we all face due to the nature
of our contemporary technology-centered life,
where all of us now are conditioned to kind of prefer
One.
moat interaction to direct personal interaction, right?
It's sort of safer to watch things
from a good safe distance, right?
It's sort of, I curiously, right?
And, you know, this goes across all,
I mean, not to get graphic family show,
but you look at statistics now.
Younger people now are far less prone
have actual physical
relationships with each other, preferring rather to just look at things on the internet.
Yeah. Right? Because it's sort of safer to be remote and distant. And so that can happen
to our religion. That can happen to, to us in the spiritual realm also, where we want to have this kind of
internet-based or just mental-based reading books-based kind of idea that doesn't, you know,
Get into a room.
with a bunch of other people and taste and smell and and be with each other and focus on the sacraments
and on the transformation of our lives and confession and repentance and all of those things, right?
They don't let you you can't stay up above it you have to get down in it right to get there.
And I think this is not unrelated to what we were talking about tonight because what we were talking
about tonight is that as we're going to celebrate.
in two days that Christ, the one who reigns on the
Cherubic throne, the one who sits and throne in the heavens on the
cherubim above the skies, that the heavenly man became the man from heaven, that
he was born and put in an animal food trough in a cave as a tiny baby and lived a
life of rejection and suffering because he did not
remain up above us, but he came down with us and became one of us and suffered alongside
us and rejoiced alongside us, mourned alongside us, celebrated weddings alongside us, embraced the
totality of our human life.
And so a big part of the way that we find salvation, we find our spiritual selves and our spiritual
renewing and healing.
and what we call theosis and deification in Christ
is through truly discovering and embracing
our humanity the way Christ did
and embracing it not only in ourselves
but in other people around us.
Because the truth is,
the things that we really want in life
to be free from fear,
to have a sense of meaning and purpose in our life,
to have the brokenness in us fixed,
to have the wounds in us healed.
to grow strong and experience love and joy and peace and all of those good things
will never happen by ourselves in a room in front of a computer screen.
It won't happen.
To get those things you have to be willing not only to get into the trenches and be around people,
not only to come to church and to the church community and go out into the world,
right, taking Christ with us.
Christ tells us we have to be willing to die.
the way he was. We have to be willing to suffer. We have to be willing potentially to become
martyrs because taking that risk, not all of us will become martyrs, right? Not all
as well. In fact, Lord willing, few of us will, but that willingness, that sort of risk-taking,
right? That being willing to risk and give up our lives in this world is what gives us
the life of the world to come.
Is it what helps us find the one thing that we truly need?
And so it's not just a question of finding a way to bridge that gap, it's imperative
that we do, right?
What we talk about on this show is like we're standing on a hill and we're describing
the landscape to you, right?
If you're seeing the layout.
But if you just stay at a distance and stand there, you're not going to experience
any of the good things that we're describing.
You've got to go down the hill,
you've got to go into the town.
And not everything there is going to be beautiful
and pretty and pleasant, right?
But all of the good things that are there
are going to come to you when you're willing to brave it
and you're willing to do it,
and you're willing to potentially sacrifice for it.
So that's what I wanted to say to wrap this up.
I hope that helps answer the question.
I'm sure I will be informed.
whether it did or did.
And we could revisit, I'll get a message from the back cave,
regarding whether that was satisfactory.
But it's critically important that at Christmas,
we remember that the path that leads us to the glory
in which Christ lives now is the path that leads us
through his humiliation, his humbling himself,
and is following the path of the cross and is
that's the way that we need to go.
Amen. Amen.
Well, that is our show for tonight and for this year.
Thank you very much for listening.
If you didn't get a chance to call in during the live broadcast,
we would like to hear from you either via email at Lordofspiritsatationfaith.com.
You can message us at our Lordofspirits podcast, Facebook page.
We do read everything but can't respond to everything.
everything and we do save some of what you send for possible use in future episodes.
and join us for our live broadcast on the second and fourth Thursdays of the month at
7 p.m. Eastern 4 p.m. Pacific.
Next time we're doing another all Q and A episode, so get ready to tell us your darkest
secrets.
And if you are on Facebook, you can like our page, join our discussion group, leave reviews
and ratings everywhere but most importantly, share this show with a friend whom you know
is going to love it.
And finally, be sure to go to ancientfaith.com, stroke support and help make sure we and
lots of other AFR podcasters stay on the air.
And you give to ancient faith you can help feed
Father Andrews children for the price of a cup of coffee a day. Amen. Thank you, good night,
God bless you, Mary Christmas, and may you have a wonderful and excellent and holy New Year.
You've been listening to The Lord of Spirits with Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew
Stephen Damick and Father Stephen De Young, a listener-supported presentation of ancient faith radio.
and I be
He held and I heard the voice of many angels round about the throne and the beasts and
the elders and the number of them was 10,000 times 10,000 than thousands of thousands,
seeing with a loud voice worthy as the land that was slain to receive power and riches and
wisdom and strength and honor and glory and blessing.
Revelation chapter 5 verses 11-12.
This is a lamp for today, understanding the Old Testament with Jesus and the Apostles.
Join Dr. Edith Humphrey in reading Old Testament passages designed to bring to life the new
Testament readings in the Divine Liturgy.
Here's Dr. Humphrey.